<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fruitfull and necessary sermon, specially concernyng almes geuing, preached the Twisday [sic] in Easter weeke The yere of our Lord. 1572. at S. Maries Spittle. By Thomas Drant, bachelor in diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Drant, Thomas, b. 1601 or 2.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125321</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898365</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132003</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73859)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132003)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2061:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fruitfull and necessary sermon, specially concernyng almes geuing, preached the Twisday [sic] in Easter weeke The yere of our Lord. 1572. at S. Maries Spittle. By Thomas Drant, bachelor in diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Drant, Thomas, b. 1601 or 2.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Iohn Daye, dwelling ouer Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1572]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: "A sermon preached at S. Maries Spittle."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div rend="roman" type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132003:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132003:1"/>
            <p>A fruitfull and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Sermon, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially concernyng Almes geuing, preached the Twiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in Eaſter Weeke. The yere of our Lord. 1572. at S. Maries Spittle.</p>
            <p rend="blackletterType">By <hi rend="roman">Thomas Drant,</hi> Bachelor in Diuinitie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi rend="italic">Micah. 6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">God</hi> told thee (O ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) what good is, and what the Lord doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of thee: certainely to do that is iuſt, to loue pityeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to walke humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy God.</p>
            </q>
            <p rend="italic">¶ Imprinted at London by Iohn Daye, dwelling ouer Alderſgate.</p>
            <p>Cum gratia &amp; Priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</p>
         </div>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:132003:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132003:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the right honorable Syr Fraunces Knolls Knyght, Treaſurer of her Maieſties houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and one of the moſt honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble priuy Counſel, grace, and peace from the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt with increaſe of all Godly honour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man can well Iudge of that which he knoweth not, and of that which he knoweth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may iudge moſt fitly: Your honour both heard this Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for your learnynge you can iudge of it, and for your vertuous zeale to God, and your common wealth you will not iudge amiſſe of it. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with a very good will I geue, and preſent it vnto your honors patronage.</p>
            <p>This Sermon hath three ſpecialties in it. The firſt is it ſpeaketh, &amp; pleadeth much for the relief of pouertie. Secondly, it is earneſt for the ſaftie of the Prince, &amp; weale publicke as it now is: Thirdly it is tarte, &amp; vehement agaynſt ſinne: as bribery, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, vſury, hypocriſie, flattery, hard har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tednes, vitiouſnes, troutheleſnes. &amp;c. The firſt point no man with an honeſt face can ſpeake agaynſt. The ſecond (God be than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) as the caſe is come to paſſe, fewe, or none dare ſpeake agaynſte. The thyrde
<pb facs="tcp:132003:3"/> hath alwayes bene vnto the preachers moſt daungerous. And therfore I was to craue your honorable protection.</p>
            <p>Of my ſelfe I could with a good will haue ſuffered this treatiſe to haue gone no farther, but ſo would not other, Both Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of good vertue, and vnderſtandyng. Furthermore that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation which that learned man Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour <hi>Humfred</hi> gaue it at Paules croſſe did ſome thyng perſuade me therunto. Laſtly your honours ſo harry, &amp; ready receauyng of it hath concluded the matter.</p>
            <p>The Lord God bleſſe you (right hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cellour) and all yours, increaſe, and continue the knowledge, and loue of his truth in you. And bryng you hereafter vnto that lyfe whiche through Chriſt Ieſus aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to your for euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honours in Chriſt moſt humble to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. <hi rend="roman">Thomas Drant.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div rend="roman" type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:132003:3"/>
            <lg>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A warnyng to repentaunce.</head>
               <l>YE riche men repent you,</l>
               <l>and geue of your goodes,</l>
               <l>For if death preuent you,</l>
               <l>ye fall into floudds,</l>
               <l>Of cares, and of carkyng,</l>
               <l>of panges, and of payne,</l>
               <l>And of conſcience barkyng,</l>
               <l>for ill gotten gayne.</l>
               <l>The worme (loe) will byte you,<note place="margin">Eſay. 66. Marke. 9.</note>
               </l>
               <l>as Eſay doth tell,</l>
               <l>Gods vengeannce will ſmite you,</l>
               <l>for euer in hell.</l>
               <l>Ye praters at Preachers,</l>
               <l>that keepe ſuch a ſteare,</l>
               <l>Ye taunters of teachers</l>
               <l>your faultes do you heare.</l>
               <l>Ye pillers, and pollers,</l>
               <l>leaue mynding your mucke:</l>
               <l>And leaue gredy prowlers,</l>
               <l>from poore men to plucke.</l>
               <l>Ye great ones, and neate ones</l>
               <l>make no more delayes,</l>
               <l>Marke, Gods word, or Gods ſword</l>
               <l>will cut of your dayes.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:132003:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q xml:lang="lat">
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                     <hi>Mitte panem tuum ſuper faciem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quarum quia multitudine die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum inuenies illum.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccl. 12.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>Da partem ſeptem, aut etiam octo: non enim ſcis quid erit mali ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per terram.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>Si repletae fuerint nubes, pluuiam ſuper terram effunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: &amp; ſi ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciderit arbor ad Auſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut ſi ad Aquilonem, in locum in que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceciderit ipſa arbor, ibi erit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Caſt thy bread vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of the waters, and after many dayes thou ſhalt finde it agayne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Geue part of it vnto vij, or eight, for thou canſt not tell what ill wilbe tyde vpon the earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If the cloudes be full, they will poure out their rayne vpon the earth, if the tree fall, whether it bee to the South, or to the North, vnto what place it doth fall, there it lyeth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:132003:4"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now right honorable, &amp; welbeloued in our Lord, and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt ij yeares a gone ſence that on this day, and this houre I occupyed this place. Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which tyme I can not reporte any great newes vnto you out of the world. Saue onely that ſaying of <hi>Terence:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Terence.</note> 
               <hi>Poeta cum primum. &amp;c. <hi>Terence</hi>
               </hi> when he bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt to write Poetrie perſuaded with himſelf that all the world would be in loue with his doings, but it fel out otherwiſe:<note place="margin">Reuel. 10. verſ. 9.</note> Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo it commeth to paſſe with the preachers of the worde of God. The word of God is ſwete as hony in their mouth. But it is bitter in their belly, men begyn with ioy and clappyng of handes, But if they ſticke to the word in continuaunce it wil repleniſhe their belly, &amp; their bones with bitternes. But, for that there is ſo great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of you come forth to heare, and it ſéemeth that your deſire is great to know what you are come forth to heare, I will therefore tell you. This text that I doe meane to entreate of is onely for almes, and for openyng of your bowels, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng relief vnto the poore. And becauſe I would put it in ſuch order that ye might
<pb facs="tcp:132003:5"/> the better beare it away. I will deuide it into theſe braunches.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt that almes muſt be geuen, &amp; how it muſt be geuen.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly to whom it muſt be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and what muſt be geuen.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, why it muſt be geuen.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I do halfe diſtruſt that theſe ſpeches of myne wilbe in vayne, and come backe agayne vnto me, euen as the Prophet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay ſaith? <hi>Domine quis credet auditui noſtro <hi>Lorde who will beleue that whiche I haue heard?</hi>
               </hi> For it is an hard perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to perſuade agaynſt money, and it is as much to ſome to departe from their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the poore, as to pull out their eyes and caſt them away, or cut of their legges and geue them away. Yet I cannot but comfort my ſelfe in God, For theſe that haue the eares to heare me ſhall heare me. And that I may do it to the better fruite of you here aſſembled together vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glory of God in heauen: I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to aſſiſte me with your good and deuout prayers. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now welbeloued, if it pleaſe you to
<pb facs="tcp:132003:5"/> ſée ouer with me the contentes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of this péece of ſcripture, I will geue you this vew for your better knowledge, Firſt, that almes ought to be geuen, and how, which is conteined in theſe wordes <hi>Mitte panem</hi> &amp; <hi>Da partem.</hi> The ſecond, what ought to be geuen, which is in this worde <hi>Panis <hi>bread.</hi>
               </hi> And to whom we ought to geue <hi>vpon the face of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to vij. and viij.</hi> Why we ſhould geue <hi>becauſe after many dayes we ſhall find it againe.</hi> Secondly, <hi>becauſe we cannot tell what ill may be chaunce vpon the earth.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>becauſe cloudes and trees are bounteous, and liberall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And touchyng the firſt point that we muſt geue almes, I cannot but maruell that men are ſo ſlow, &amp; hard affectioned in geuyng conſideryng the great threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyngs of God to thoſe that wil not geue,<note place="margin">Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt hard harted<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> &amp; the promiſes of God to thoſe that will geue. Touchyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> threatnyngs of God, Let vs thinke thus. <hi>1.</hi> Iohn. <hi>3. <hi>Qui habet facultates huius mundi. &amp;c.</hi> He that hath the ſubſtaunce of this world, and ſeeth his brother want how can the loue of God be in hym.</hi> So that this Scripture threatneth, that God will loue him no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that doth ſée his brother in neceſſitie,
<pb facs="tcp:132003:6"/> and will not releue him. The weight of this threatnyng is the loſſe of the loue of God: the whiche loue is ſo great that when as the mother forgetteth her child, yet the loue of God continueth ſtil to his beloued. And it is ſurely to be thought that thoſe that are verely beloued of god, cannot by depth or hight, heate, or cold, or any violente meanes be ſeperated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.<note place="margin">The firſt threatnyng is the loſſe of the loue of God.</note> We may ſée likewiſe a preſident of our puniſhment for not geuyng almes. In that rich perſon which S. Luke ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of chap. xvi. The which rich man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his death to his greater grief ſée La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus who he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned in one haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of reſt with Abraham: Agayne he could not helpe his frendes by warnyng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their liues, &amp; that which was worſt of all other, he was tormented in fire. (I am tormented in this fire ſayth he.) Fire burneth, ſcaldeth, ſcorcheth &amp; torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth, and if the world will not beleue this, Let them do as S. Thomas did into Chriſtes woundes, put in their handes, and féele. But the world beleueth that there is no fire, But I beleue that it tormenteth, and that it wilbe founde ſo. Further we read Math. xxv. Then he will ſay to thoſe that be on the left hand: <hi>go ye curſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me
<pb facs="tcp:132003:6"/> into fire which was prepared from the beginning. When I was a ſtraunger ye dyd not receiue me. &amp;c.</hi> So that the fire is not onely hote, but it is euerlaſtyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hote. <hi>Martine Luther</hi> ſayd, that hee could not reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber God the father with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out horror and feare, except he remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred alſo Ieſus Chriſt. Then,<note place="margin">Hell exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie.</note> the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the paynes of hell be without Chriſt intollerable. But ſpecially eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hath all terrour in it. If that a man ſhould be preſte with a ſtone as bigge as the whole earth, and euery thouſand yeare a byrde ſhould come, and cary away but one bilfull of this ſtone, yet in tyme the ſtone would wholy be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed away. But that whiche is euer can neuer ceaſe. Let therfore fire, and eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the fire, exhorte you to be mercyfull vnto the poore.</p>
            <p>If you will rather be moued by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, God promiſeth lviij.<note place="margin">Promiſes.</note> of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſay. <hi>If thou doeſt breake thy bread vnto the poore, and poure out thy hart, Thy light ſhall riſe in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and thy dymnes ſhalbe as the none tyde, &amp; God ſhal euer gide thee. He ſhall fill thy ſoule in all drouthes, and he ſhal fatten thy bones, and thou
<pb facs="tcp:132003:7"/> ſhalt be as a moiſt garden and as a fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine whoſe water ſhall neuer faile.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne it is ſayd <hi>come ye bleſſed of my father poſſeſſe the kyngdome prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for you before the foundations of the worlde were layd. When I was a ſtraunger ye did receiue me. &amp;c.</hi> So that the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen remaineth to thoſe that harbor ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers, and cloth the naked, and do the like workes of compaſſion. The pleaſures of heauen are ioyfull pleaſures, our toung cannot ſpeake how ioyfull, nor our eare heare, nor our hart thinke in what exceſſe they be. The greater the ioyes they be, the more they exhorte vs to be liberall. Geue therefore: for euen of it ſelfe it is goodly to geue. Chriſte ſayth it is more bleſſed to geue then to take. The noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of creatures co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in geuyng: the Sunne in geuyng his light, the Moone her light, the ſtarres their light, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloudes their water, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trées their fruite, the earth her graſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> graſſe her floures. Al good na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures haue ben well ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of for geuing. <hi>Saluſt</hi> ſaith <hi>Caeſar</hi> by helping by reliuing &amp; forgeuing got renome. <hi>Auguſtus Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> thought that day to be loſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he gratified no man with ſome pleaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:132003:7"/> But you wil ſay how ſhould a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue? <hi>Mitte.</hi> That is, caſt it, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s almes muſt be caſt. In caſting there are two thyngs. The will of the doing, &amp; the readynes in doing. Touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil it ſelf, <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith in his offices, That which is wel done is therfore well done becauſe it is willingly done. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the readines in geuing, we muſt caſt it. We muſt do eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as God doth to vs, if we ſéeke the kyngdome of heauen all thynges are caſt vnto vs. The true obedience of God doth not prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g,<note place="margin">Gene. 7. Gene. 17. Iohn. 10.</note> or driue of from tyme to tyme, Noath the ſame moment that he was commaunded entred he, and his into the Arke. Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed his houſe in the ſame day he was appointed. Chriſt ſayd to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, come and ſée, and ſtreight way they came and ſawe. Iacob beyng commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to goe out of his countrey hoiſed vp his féete, and went. It is commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the xx. of the Prouerbes that we ſhould not ſay go, and come agayne to morrow. Iames ſaith iiij. <hi>that we know not what wilbe to morow. Gregory Nazianzen</hi> ſayth in his Epigrames. That when he had once loſt the good tenour of lyfe, gray heares was gotte about his head or hee could recouer it agayne. If we begyn to
<pb facs="tcp:132003:8"/> harden our hart towardes the poore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng young. If we do not caſt our bread readely, but driue their hungry mouthes away greuouſly, gray heares will come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our heads, or we can come backe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the way of pitie, and compaſſion.</p>
            <p>And as we muſt caſt our bread for our owne part ſo recheleſly that the one hand ſhall not know what the other doth: So muſt we do it ſo equally in the behalfe of our poore neighbours, that there may be a diuiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for ſo it is ment in this word <hi>Diſtribue,</hi> or <hi>Da partes:</hi> that is deuide it, or part it.<note place="margin">Iob. 31. Tobi. 2.</note> So Iob and Tobi are repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Scripture to haue broken their bread. Our people haue not all one belly. As <hi>Nero</hi> wiſhed that the people of Rome might haue all one necke.<note place="margin">Indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in aimes geuyng.</note> One chimney beyng full of fire an other may be cold. One potte beyng full of licour an other may be dry. And one poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s belly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng full, An other poore mans ſtomacke may be knawyng, and hungry. That is a good ſtomacke whiche ſendeth out nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment vnto all partes of the body. And that is a good common wealth, which loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to euery member of the common wealth. For as it is good for euery one that all ſhould be looked vnto, ſo it is good
<pb facs="tcp:132003:8"/> for the whole ſtate of the weale publicke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertulian</hi> ſayth, where there is no Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, there is no peace. And it is true, for not onely beggers as <hi>Irus</hi> and <hi>Vliſſes</hi> do fall foorth for lacke of equalitie, but it goeth further, and higher: For <hi>Eſaw</hi> wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed his fathers death, becauſe he had ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all away vnto <hi>Iacob.</hi> So <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſayth in <hi>Lucan.</hi> That <hi>certaine priuate men had caught all the wealth into theyr hands.</hi> But that is the ſpeciall, and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt hart breake, when as thynges are ſo vniuſtly deuided, that worthy men haue litle, And vnworthy men haue much, as when great learned <hi>S. Auſten</hi> is Byſhop of little <hi>Hippo,</hi> and litle learned <hi>Aurelius</hi> Byſhop of great <hi>Carthage.</hi> Other ſome expound this word <hi>Da partes,</hi> rather thus <hi>Da parte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> That is, geue part. And the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you wil aſke me how much a man muſt geue of his ſubſtaunce. I will aunſwere with <hi>Nazie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>zen</hi> out of his Epigrames.<note place="margin">How much a man muſt geue.</note> 
               <hi>Geue all or moſt, or halfe, or litle leſſe.</hi> And out of <hi>Tobi</hi> the iiij. chapter: and <hi>if thou haſt much geue much, if litle, geue aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as thou canſt.</hi> And out of Luke the <hi>3.</hi> chap. <hi>He that hath two coates let hym geue one to him that hath not, &amp; of meate likewiſe.</hi> Here if ye deſire that
<pb facs="tcp:132003:9"/> I ſhould quallifie this ſtreight commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement: ſurely I will not, our own hard hartes are ready inough to finde excuſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But I will let the commaundement ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hard as it doth, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to your owne perils and quallifie it as you can.</p>
            <p>Let vs go forward, and ſée what w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt geue, and to whom we muſt geue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The texte ſayth we muſt geue <hi>bread</hi> Bread therefore is the thyng we muſt geue.<note place="margin">What and to whom we muſt geue.</note> In the which there be two thynges to be noted, the one is to the taker, &amp; the other to the geuer. To the taker as thus. Bread will ſerue beggers. Beggers may not be choſers. They are bold beggers that in Stangate hole take me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s horſes by the heades, &amp; aſke money, beggers may not be of the opinion of the Anabaptiſtes that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s goodes are commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers muſt bee content to take vp their croſſe euery day, &amp; to ſuffer. And to know that mans nature is ſatiſfied with a litle. Agayne here the geuer may learne to geue fréely. The thyng that he geueth is but bread. The Hebrew word <hi>Lahem</hi> ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifieth, bread or fruit. Bread is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruite of the earth. The earth geueth it vs, and therfore we may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better geue it agayne. It wilbe ſayd that bread in this place ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth
<pb facs="tcp:132003:9"/> as in the Lords prayer all things neceſſarye.<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> I will not greatly ſtande a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte it. Howbeit I muſt néedes ſay it is worthy to be noted. That the fare and the there of the old tyme is contayned in bread, &amp; the drinke of the old tyme is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in water: But in this thyng as in other thynges the ſimplicitie of the olde world is quite fled, and new thynges and corrupt thynges are crept in. In old time father <hi>Iacob</hi> deſired hee might haue but bread in his iourney.<note place="margin">Gene. 28.</note> In this new tymes it is with vs as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaid it was with his Monkes.<note place="margin">New fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions and old faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s quyte con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</note> 
               <hi>I maruell</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that ſuch inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peraunce is growen amongſt my Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes in their eatynges and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynges. All thynges are dreſſed with ſuch he defulnes and craft.</hi> The pallat is intiſed with new ſawſes. <q rend="margDblQuotes">Who can tell by how many meanes egges are toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; vexed, with what a do they are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned out, and halfe turned out, made ſoft made hard, and deminiſhed, fried, roſted, ferſed, with other meates, without other meates? The ſtomacke doth declare it ſelfe to haue inough by often belchyng: but yet theyr curioſitie is not ſatiſfied whileſt that the eyes are fild on with co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lore and the pallat with taſtes. The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
<pb facs="tcp:132003:10"/> ſtomacke to whom neither colors do ſhyne, nor taſtes are daintie, whileſt it is compelled to receaue all thynges, it is rather ouerwhelmed then refreſhed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In old tyme their drinke was contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the name of water. In the new tyme it is as <hi>S. Barnard</hi> ſaith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> drinke of his Monkes.<note place="margin">In libro A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologetico de Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis.</note> 
               <hi>Primo vinum lymphatum non admittitur &amp;c. <hi>Firſt of all we can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde no water in our wine.</hi>
               </hi> We haue all gotten weake ſtomackes. I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſpeake it. <q rend="margDblQuotes">Thou ſhalt ſée in one dynner halfe cupfulles of wyne caryed backe againe. And diuers kindes of wine are rather ſmelled to, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of. Not ſo much dro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as taſted: at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth after wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty taſtyng, &amp; ſwift allowyng, they choſe one whiche is moſt ſtrong, and heddy. Agayne they myngle their wynes with hony. Do they that for weaknes of their ſtomacke? truly I do ſée none other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in their ſo doing, but onely that they may drinke more, or with more pleaſure.</q> But when the vaynes are full of wyne, and doe frote and beate all the head o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, a man riſing ſo from the table, what other luſt then hath he but to go to ſlepe? And when he is come to his bed, he doth morne not the ſinne of his dronkennes:
<pb facs="tcp:132003:10"/> but becauſe his ſtomacke is gone that he can eate no more.<note place="margin">Gene. 18.</note> In old tyme Aungels were wont to go on foote, In new tyme as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Gene. 23. &amp;. 38.</note> ſeruauntes ryde on horſebacke. In old time father <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> traueled farre iorneyes with a ſtaffe on their backe: In theſe new tymes we cannot traueile from one village to an other, But we haue a ſword, &amp; a buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, a Tucke, and a Targette, a dagger &amp; a raper, a muſkete, a cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer, a currier, a hargabuſh, and an halfe hacke, a piſtol &amp; a piſtollet, a dagge and a ſnapehanche. I ſay the mallice, &amp; curioſitie of new times hath driuen awaye the ſimplicitie of olde tymes.<note place="margin">Gene. 27.</note> In old tyme my Lady <hi>Rebecka</hi> came ridyng to her new huſband on a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels backe, In new tyme our Ladyes haue waggyns, couches, and horſelitters ſoft, ſilke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſewtable. In old time the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarke <hi>Iudas</hi> dyd know the harlot <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> by her apparell,<note place="margin">Gene. 24.</note> In the new time ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matrons are ſo lightly apparelled, or harlots ſo grauely, that thinges are blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and confounded. In old tyme the Prophetes were knowne by their appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 13 Read Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary.</note> As that Prophet whiche was ſlayne by the Lyon, In the new tyme becauſe ſome godly men haue a remorſe in wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng
<pb facs="tcp:132003:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:132003:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:132003:12"/> ſome kynde of apparell. Therefore other ſome of the Miniſterie pretendyng the ſame Religion, will go brauely lyke mynions.<note place="margin">Gene. 37.</note> In old tyme <hi>Ioſeph</hi> dreamed a dreame that he ſhould be in great eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; that hys brethren ſhould worſhyp him, and told it them. In new tyme it is thought a ſufferaigne wiſedome to be of an hollow, and cloſe hart, and to diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble in all thynges.<note place="margin">Gene. 39.</note> In old tyme <hi>Ioſeph</hi> could not be pulled by his miſtres to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her, In new time it is a certaine kinde of trade for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to riſe vp by pullyng their miſtres.<note place="margin">Gene. 49.</note> In old tyme <hi>Ioſeph</hi> forgaue his brethren, that had abuſed hym, and done hym ſo many iniuries. In this new time there is nothing but fierce reuengement in all ſortes. Euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taketh his felow by the throt, And if there lacke iuſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, they will picke quarels. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> Martyr. They cried out in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of doctrine <hi>LET OLD THINGS PREVAILE.</hi> So I put you in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the ſimplicitie of the old world. In matters of maners doe now cry out Let old thynges preuayle. And this much of that point, what we muſt geue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">To whom we muſt geue.</note>Let vs now likewiſe briefly ſée to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we muſt geue. The text ſayth in the firſt
<pb facs="tcp:132003:12"/> lyne <hi>vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of the waters.</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d line <hi>to vij. or to viij.</hi> You wil ſay you do not know what that ſaying meaneth <hi>vppon the face of the waters.</hi> I thinke ſo. A good deuine may miſſe the expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this place. I will not take vppon me to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d it. But will tell you how others haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon it. And firſt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalio</hi> commeth into my mynde, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth it thus. <hi>Caſt thy bread vpon the face of the waters.</hi> That is, <hi>vnto moiſt places.</hi> By moiſt places he ſemeth to meane ſuch places, and perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as will be fruitfull, and thriue by the caſtyng of our bread vnto them. But this expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me thinketh ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be true. Becauſe that in this world no man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tell what ſucceſſe will come vnto man. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth in the ix. chap. of Eccle. <hi>All thynges fall out alike vnto all men. One chaunce is to the iuſt and vniuſt. The good, &amp; cleane and the vncleane. To him that ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, and to hym that doth not ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Euen as the good is, euen ſo is he that doth ſinne. And as he is that doth ſweare, ſo is he that is afeard to take an othe.</hi> Agayne he ſaid, <hi>I ſee that in ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng it did not preuayle to bee ſwift. Nor in battaile to be ſtrong, that wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:132003:13"/> men doe not alwayes get their bread, nor witty men riches. And that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men are not alwayes in fauour. But tyme, and chaunce preuayleth in euery thyng.</hi> I do hereby therfore ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that we ſhould not ſtand ſtill vpon conſultyng, whether the partie that we wold geue to, would thriue, or not thriue, be lucky or not lucky, it were but a vayne conſultation, becauſe man cannot tell it. And therfore I will let ſlip this expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. An other expoſition there is. That to caſt thy bread vpon the face of the waters, is to ſend it ouer the Seas. And if this be true as it is not all together vnlickly: We may ſée how large, and farre ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a thing charitie is, whiche the great and huge body of the monſtruous Sea can not diſſunder. They be our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours alſo which dwell beyond the ſeas. For charitie ſtretcheth to the compaſſion towardes all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Charitie is not tyed to a few but ſpreadeth farre.</note> And if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our power be ſuch, we are bounde to reliue thoſe that bee beyond the Seas: then this is but a couetous folly to perſuade our ſelues, That we are not bound in conſcience to geue any thyng out of our owne Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes. Nay this is a forcible argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them that prouide onely for their
<pb facs="tcp:132003:13"/> owne houſholdes kinredes, and families. But ſpecially agaynſt thoſe which caſting away all other care, doe make their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their onely God. And thinke them ſelues borne onely to them ſelues: men moſt farre of from the obſeruyng of this precept. <hi>Send or caſt thy bread vppon the face of the waters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is yet alſo an other expoſition, and that is to caſt our bread vpon moyſt faces, aſmuch to ſay as faces of teares:<note place="margin">Teares.</note> or weping faces, &amp; in déede teares are great cauſe of compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſpecially the teares y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> riſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beggers eyes are of great force, &amp; muſt néedes be regarded. If the teares of <hi>Eſaw</hi> that wept for loſſe of goodes, if of <hi>Pompey</hi> that wept at the ſight of the Citie called <hi>Cacobaſilia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 17.</note> of <hi>Dauid</hi> that wept for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of one city, &amp; two wiues, Of <hi>Alexander</hi> that wept for the ſight of a Tragedy, of <hi>Metellus</hi> that wept be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was not at the wynnyng of <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mydy,</hi> If the teares which riſe of foyles, of kyndenes, of vnkyndnes, of percell loſſes, if the teares of vnkyndnes be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and remembred: what ſay you to thoſe teares that riſe of beggery, of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and of hunger. O what ſhould a man ſay to thoſe faces, which be made moyſt
<pb facs="tcp:132003:14"/> thorough the ſtyng of hunger. Hunger hath moſt bitter, and ſharpe effectes. It caſteth in, all extremities. Prouerb .xxvij. <hi>To an hungry ſoule euery bitter thyng is ſweete,</hi> it made the Apoſtles glad to eate <hi>the eares of corne. Dauid</hi> glad to eate the <hi>ſhewe bread. Lazarus</hi> glad to eate <hi>cromes. Elias</hi> glad of <hi>meale, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutus</hi> the <hi>Turkes</hi> elder brother to lyue long with <hi>wyldinges.</hi> In the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> it made the <hi>mother to eate her child</hi> In the <hi>waylynges of Ieremy</hi> it made people to eate theyr owne <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 41.</note> It made the people crye vnto <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao for bread.</hi> It made ſo great an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in <hi>Samaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kinges. 2</note> that the <hi>hed of an aſſe,</hi> and a litle <hi>Pigeons dong</hi> were dearely ſold,<note place="margin">Eſay. 51.</note> it made them <hi>to ſound and to lye in the ſtretes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apocal. 6.</note> It maketh them blacke as ſute, And therfore the horſe of hunger is called the blacke horſe, And in this place is ſayd to make men to ſhed teares, and haue moyſt faces. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth that <hi>God nombred all his teares in a bottell. Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uides</hi> teares were worthy to be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. But, if euer teares were worthy to be nombred, the teares that are ſhed for famine, howſoeuer me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neglect them, are vndoubtedly gathered together into gods
<pb facs="tcp:132003:14"/> bottell, and thence they rayne as waters out of violles in way of reuengement of thoſe that wil not looke vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth not teares, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng.</note> Teares are the laſt thyng that man or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can moue by. And therfore poore <hi>Dido</hi> beyng at the laſt caſt deſireth <hi>Aeneas</hi> by her teares to bee good to her: where teares moue not, there nothyng moueth. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you, good people, by the fayntyng of theſe poore men, by their blacke faces, by their cryinges, by their ſownynges, by their teares to be good, and mercyfull vn-them. And to caſt your bread vpon their moyſt faces.</p>
            <p>The laſt expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this text, is. That a man ſhould geue his almes, though he haue no more hope to recouer it, then he hath that whiche hee caſteth vppon the face of the runnyng water. This ſence I thinke to bee nereſt vnto the truth. And this ſence exhorteth vs vehemently to be francke, and almoſt deſperate in geuing, and taketh away almoſt all excuſe of hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng, and retainyng. Furthermore if ye deſire to know to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhould geue, the text wil tell you, to <hi>vij.</hi> or to <hi>viij.</hi> That is to a great no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. The Scripture ſaith, <hi>geue to euery one that aſketh,</hi> ſo God in the begynnyng of the Geneſis gaue
<pb facs="tcp:132003:15"/> herbes &amp; other foode to euery liuing thing. Euery common wealth that letteth any member of it to periſhe for hunger, is in ſo doyng the worſe, and more vncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble common wealth. But, there be ſuch doubtes that you cannot be perſuaded to parte with any thyng you haue,<note place="margin">Obiections of the hard hart.</note> becauſe a man partyng now from his money to a poore man, it is as a man ſhould caſt a thyng into the water, it will be loſt, and it wil not be remembred. Touchyng that point that you thinke it ſhalbe loſt, ye ſhal here more afterward.<note place="margin">The do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynges of men are ſoone for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten.</note> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of your good déedes thus beſtowed ye ſhal here preſent. I marueile what this world can do wherby it ſhalbe reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred? Is not the place of Paradiſe it ſelfe, and the iiij. riuers cleane forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where they were? If Paradiſe be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſhall earthly remembraunces re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine? Who doth now beare in mynde what maner of apparell <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> or <hi>Salomon</hi> did weare? Or what were the faſhions in attyre in thoſe dayes?<note place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> Who hath in mynde what meate the rich glot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton dyd eate? is not the Cheualry of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forgotten?<note place="margin">True al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes neuer forgotten.</note> bookes and booke wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters forgotten? Dwellynges, feaſtes, ſhewes, Royalties, ioyes, and ieſtes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten?
<pb facs="tcp:132003:15"/> all thynges in this world are, or ſhalbe forgotten. But God is not vniuſt that hee will forget the worke,<note place="margin">Hebr. 6.</note> and loue which you haue ſhewed in his name.</p>
            <p>Yet there is an other doubt that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt geue to ſo many, to vij. or to viij.<note place="margin">An other excuſe.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las will they ſay, we ſhalbe ouerwhelmed with nomber. A man by geuing to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny beggers, hym ſelfe in tyme ſhalbe a begger. <hi>Dauid</hi> aunſwered to this, <hi>I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſaw the iuſt man forſaken, nor hys ſeede beggyng his bread.</hi> He meaneth this, that in ſo long a lyfe as <hi>Dauid</hi> had leadd, a man ſhall ſcarce ſée that vpon an vpright harte in geuyng a man ſhalbe brought to beggery. But let vs ſée the weight of this doubt, thou ſayeſt thou art afrayd to geue vnto vij, or to viij. Let me heare what y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſayeſt, is it ſo great a thing to geue vnto vij, or to viij? But y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> makeſt it no great doubt, thou thy ſelfe alone to ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vij. viij. ix. x. or xx. diſhes. To haue xx. coates, xx. houſes, xx. farmes, yea xx. Lordſhyps. If thou be a Lawyer thou art not afeard to vnder xx. poore men, or a Marchaunt to eate vp twenty Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes. Where there is no feare thou art much afearde: and where there is much feare, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art nothyng afeard. The world can euer eaſly find a ſtaffe to beate
<pb facs="tcp:132003:16"/> a dogge. The world is neuer without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, it is euer ready to finde delayes, and finde ſhiftes to kéepe in their almes. So <hi>Naball</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> made his moane to hym for relief at his hand, Though hée were a ſtarke foole otherwayes, yet he re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely founde excuſes to deny hym his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.</note> For firſt ſayth Dauid <hi>who is Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nabals excuſe.</note> or <hi>who is the ſonne of Iſa?</hi> Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſayth, that <hi>many ſeruauntes were gone a ſide from their maſter.</hi> Thirdly, that <hi>ſuch meate as hee had it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, but for him, &amp; his ſherers.</hi> Wel, go to, let vs examine theſe reaſons of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ball,</hi> and purſewe hys excuſes. <hi>Who is Dauid</hi> quoth <hi>Naball, and who is the ſonne of Iſa? Abigall</hi> a wiſe woman, the wife of <hi>Naball</hi> did know <hi>Dauid.</hi> The ſeruauntes of <hi>Naball</hi> dyd reporte very well of <hi>Dauid. Dauid</hi> had kylled great <hi>Golliath, Dauid</hi> was knowne to the Ladies of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and all <hi>Iſraell:</hi> yet <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball</hi> doth not know <hi>Dauid. Naball</hi> dyd knowe <hi>Dauid,</hi> but <hi>Naball</hi> would not know <hi>Dauid.</hi> Deafe eares in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, deafe eares in aduerſitie. Neuer in miſerie doth any <hi>Naball</hi> know any <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</hi> Let vs ſée this ſecond excuſe, Many ſeruauntes bee gone a ſide from theyr
<pb facs="tcp:132003:16"/> maſter. <hi>Naball</hi> here ſéemeth to accuſe <hi>Dauid</hi> of goyng aſide from his maſter, that is of a ſchiſme, or rebellion, Neuer thinkyng with him ſelfe the great cruelty of his Maſter <hi>Saule,</hi> The perillous accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of <hi>Doeg,</hi> yea and at ſuch tyme as <hi>Dauid</hi> went about to aſſwage the deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe, and vnte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perat nature of <hi>Saule</hi> with pleaſaunt, and well tewned muſike, At the ſame tyme <hi>Saule</hi> went about to kyll <hi>Dauid.</hi> Theſe thynges <hi>Naball</hi> would not conſider, for ſurely <hi>Naball,</hi> and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men will to the death accuſe iuſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, rather then by their almes they wil relief the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Nabals</hi> third excuſe was y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion as hée had was for him, &amp; his ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and this excuſe is alſo worthy to be thought vpon. Let vs conſider <hi>Dauid</hi> &amp; <hi>Naball,</hi> what was <hi>Dauid?</hi> as I ſayd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, a triumpher vpon <hi>Golliath,</hi> a man of wyde renome, &amp; vnder God the glory of <hi>Iſraell.</hi> What is <hi>Dauid?</hi> At this inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t when he made his ſupplication to <hi>Nabal</hi> a poore Gentleman, yet a Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tleman, yea a very honeſt godly &amp; famous gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What was <hi>Dauid?</hi> like to be a Prince, a Kyng, and his ſéede to rule <hi>in ſecula ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Now what was <hi>Naball?</hi> His name ſayth, he was a foole. His good wife ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:132003:17"/> he was a foole, and his maners proclai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med hym to bee a foole <hi>in ſecula ſeculorum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Yet fooliſh <hi>Nabal</hi> and his fooliſh ſhearers muſt haue all. And <hi>Dauid</hi> and his godly company muſt lacke all: Thus what for feare to caſt our bread into the water or for feare to geue it vnto to many as to vij. or viij. or els for other excuſes which wordly <hi>Nabals</hi> can inuent: <hi>Dauid</hi> and poore men are moſt ſparyngly refreſhed, charity is quenched, and we dare not caſt our bread vppon the face of the waters. But theſe doubtes are no doubtes, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we ſhould not geue,<note place="margin">The firſt reaſon why we ſhould geue.</note> but the reaſons that folow are great reaſons wherefore we ſhuld geue, becauſe after many dayes we ſhall finde it agayne. And here the world can doubt nothyng, but that we ſhall finde it agayne. For God ſayth in this place <hi>we ſhall finde it agayne.</hi> In Eccl. <hi>3.</hi> It is ſayd, That <hi>the Lord which doth recompence fauour for fauour wilbe myndefull hereafter. That hee whiche geueth in tyme of his fall ſhall receaue relief agayne.</hi> In Pſalme xlj. It is ſayd. <hi>Bleſſed is he which doth conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the poore and nedy. Becauſe in the day of neceſsitie the Lord will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him. The Lord will kepe him and
<pb facs="tcp:132003:17"/> quicken hym. He ſhal be bleſſed in the land, and ſhall not be geuen ouer into the handes of hys enemies. The Lord ſhall prompt hym vp in the bed of his ſorrow. And turne his couch in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie.</hi> So by theſe, and many other places it is playne, that God ſayeth we ſhall finde our almes agayne.<note place="margin">The truth of the word of God pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth that we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue our almes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.</note> Neither ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hard harted man ſticke here, except he will doubt whether Gods wordes bée true or no, The whiche if he do let him knowe what <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth Pſalme. xciij. ſaying, <hi>thy teſtimonies are very true.</hi> Eſay ſayth xlv. chap. <hi>De ore egreſſum eſt verbum meum &amp; no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuertetur. <hi>The word is gone out of my mouth and it ſhall not returne. 2.</hi>
               </hi> Cor. <hi>1.</hi> It is ſayd: <hi>All the promiſes in Chriſt be yea &amp; amen.</hi> And this is true of all Gods other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, They bee all yea and amen,<note place="margin">Gene. 49.</note> Old <hi>Iacob</hi> promiſed that Chriſt would come ſo it fell out it was yea and amen.</p>
            <p>For God fulfilled that which he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 15.</note> He promiſed <hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> ſéede lyke the Starres from the ſky: It came ſo to paſſe as we read in third booke of the kynges:<note place="margin">3. Kinges. 3</note> 
               <hi>I am</hi> ſayth Salomon <hi>in the middeſt of this people, whiche can not be no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred nor compted.</hi> His pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
<pb facs="tcp:132003:18"/> that he made to <hi>Sara</hi> was true. Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> promiſe that hee made in xxx. of Exodus in deliueryng hys people out of <hi>Egyp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was true, That whiche he promiſed t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ioſua</hi> of the wynnyng of the Citie <hi>Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and all the kynges that conſpired agayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him was true likewiſe.<note place="margin">Ioſua. 8.</note> 
               <note place="margin">1. Kings. 13 3. Kinges. 3 1. Samu. 65 1. Sam. 4.</note> He promiſed <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid</hi> his kyngdome, <hi>Salomon</hi> wiſedome <hi>Pharao</hi> deſtruction by water, <hi>Saule</hi> loſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his kyngdome, <hi>Helye</hi> necke breake <hi>Salomon</hi> the deuiding of his kingdome And all theſe proued true, all and euer the wordes of God ſhalbe found certain that is yea &amp; amen. Neither are we alon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to venture of the certeintie of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſes. They haue bene that haue ven<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tured long before, and with great ieper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bare word of God.<note place="margin">Gene. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> ventured to forſake the acquaintaunce o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his youth, his kinſfolke, and fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and and to leaue that which he had long ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with his eyes, to go to that whiche he ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſaw, So ventured he to ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kyng <hi>Gederlaomer</hi> and his felow kings.<note place="margin">Gene. 14.</note> And further to kill his own ſonne, and all this vpon the bare word of God.<note place="margin">Gene. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Noe</hi> ventu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red to defray great ſommes of money for the buyldyng of an Arke, All the whole world laughyng on him to ſcorne, by the
<pb facs="tcp:132003:18"/> onely warraunt of Gods worde, <hi>Moſes</hi> ventured to forſake the kynred, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quayntaunce of <hi>Pharao,</hi> and rather to ſuffer affliction with the people of God onely for the truſt he had in that worde. And as it is ſayd in xj to the Hebr. what ſhall I more ſay? the tyme will fayle me if I ſhould rehearſe of <hi>Gedion,</hi> of <hi>Barach Sampſon, Iepth, Dauid, Samuell</hi> &amp; the Prophetes. If all theſe haue ventured, why dare not you venture? vppon mans word the world wil venture: mans word is but pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne inke and paper. Gods word is a rocke, Gods word is not ſubiect to caſualtie. Mans word is ſubiect to craft &amp; caſualtie. If therfore we venture vpon any ground, Let vs venture vpon Gods worde, why ſhould we not venture? In ſhort tyme after we muſt venture, for we muſt dye, &amp; leaue our goods we wote not to whom. So in Luke xij. <hi>Foole this night they will fetche away thy ſoule. And then that whiche thou haſt gotte whoſe ſhall it be?</hi> So in Eccle. <hi>3. I hate my labour in the whiche I haue labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnder the ſunne. Becauſe I muſt leaue it vnto a man which ſhalbe after me. And no man can tel whether he be wiſe or a foole. And yet he muſt be a
<pb facs="tcp:132003:19"/> Lord in all the labour, which I haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored vnder the ſunne.</hi> Heyres appare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I ſaye are not alwayes heyres at your death you muſt venture it, therfore now venture it. Ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture, for after many dayes ye ſhall receaue it agayn. But it forethin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God differreth your reward many dayes and that it ſhalbe long or you finde it.<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> Know you what Iob ſayth. <hi>If we take good thyngs at Gods hand, Why doe we not take ill thinges likewiſe?</hi> If we be well content y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God ſhould lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre our puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t why are we not like<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God ſhould lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g differre our ioy, &amp; reward? God ſuffered <hi>Cayne</hi> long vnpuniſhed, He ſuffered the ſinners be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſtud Cxx. yeares after he had war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned them. He ſuffered the <hi>Amorittes,</hi> whileſt their iniquitie was filled vp. He ſuffered <hi>Sodome,</hi> and <hi>Gomorra</hi> whileſt the crye of their wickednes was multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, and their ſinne was to much made haynous.<note place="margin">Eſay. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> He ſuffered <hi>Mohab</hi> iij. yeares, he threatened that the people ſhould bée ſlayne on the alter in <hi>Ierobohams</hi> dayes for their wickednes,<note place="margin">1. Kings. 13</note> yet he differred this puniſhment CC. and lx. yeares. He ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vngodly men to prolong their dayes by their malice. He ſuffereth wicked men
<pb facs="tcp:132003:19"/> to liue in great proſperitie, and to be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed honorably.<note place="margin">Eccl. 7. and 10.</note> And their ſonnes to be great men, And ryde on horſebacke. He ſuffered the rich man in S. Luke to eate and drinke euen to his death. He beareth with iniquitie in all men, and ſuffereth it long vnpuniſhed. Therfore if it be long or we finde our bread agayne, we muſt be content with it. If it greue vs that it is differred many dayes. Let vs remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo being a good, and iuſt man was vnlooked to many dayes. And therefore he crieth often <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquequo.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 6. and .13.</note> How long, how long Lord, how long, and this he crieth ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. The people of God ſayth, that they were exerciſed with miſeries euen from their youth. Godly men dye vnburied, and hee that did ſaue a Citie.<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.</note> God ſuffered hym in this worlde to bee cleane forgotten. <hi>Sara</hi> ſuffered long vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Hagar,</hi> and her ſonne, <hi>Abraham</hi> ſuffered long the iniurie of <hi>Abimileckes</hi> ſeruauntes, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſuffered longe the wronges of his brethren, and of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris. <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſuffered longe and many wrongs. <hi>Paule</hi> ſuffered lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g troubles, and wronges. The people of God Apocal. vi. cry out <hi>how long O Lord thou that art holy and true. Doeſt thou not Iudge
<pb facs="tcp:132003:20"/> and reuenge our bloud on thoſe that dwell on the earth.</hi> So that God exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth good men long in the troubles of this world,<note place="margin">Our tyme is but ſhort though trouble make it ſeme long.</note> And therfore we may be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted if after a long tyme we finde the fruit of our almes agayne. Neither be theſe dayes long dayes in déede, but in opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and though they be many dayes, yet are they but dayes. For the length of our life is not worthy to be named in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of yeares. Our life is as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſayth of hys life <hi>my dayes are but a few.</hi> Ioſeph be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng borne in the midle age of <hi>Iacob</hi> is ſayd in Scripture ſo bee the ſonne of hys old age. For a man beyng a child, is euen now at his middle age: and beyng at hys middle age is euen now at his olde age. An hundred yeares in age is but the yeares of childhode, ſo it is ſayd a child of an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeare old.<note place="margin">Eſay. 38.</note> The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> calleth lx. yeares but one moment. He tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his people he would forſake them for a moment, He meaneth lx. yeares in the captiuitie of Babilon. <hi>Paule</hi> calleth the greefes that we haue in this worlde the griefes of a moment, <hi>Dauid</hi> compareth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s life to wind, to talke, &amp; to a ſhadow: <hi>Eſay</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pareth it to the remouyng of a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle. <hi>Iob</hi> to an Egles wyng and to a
<pb facs="tcp:132003:20"/> Weuers ſhittell. So that theſe many dayes are in déede but a few dayes. Go to it frely therefore, For after a fewe dayes though you thinke them many dayes. What ſoeuer you mercyfully beſtow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the poore ye ſhall finde it agayne.</p>
            <p>There foloweth an other reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">The ſecond reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore we ſhould geue almes.</note> 
               <hi>Thou canſt not tell what wilbe tyde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the earth.</hi> So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> here <hi>Salomon</hi> ſemeth to ſay this much, There will ſome thyng fall on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth that thou knoweſt not of, if thou diddeſt know of it, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wouldeſt know, it would ſurely ſtyrre thée vp to be liberall. And that thou dooſt not know particular chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces I do not greatly blame thée. In déede <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth truly, <hi>We doe not know thynges to come.</hi> For it was not geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the Apoſtles to know tymes, &amp; the moments of times, For euen in theſe thynges where our booke lyeth open, we are deceaued for lacke of knowledge. So <hi>Gregory Nazie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>zen</hi> ſemeth not to know the true honor of Mariage.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Orat.</hi> 31.</note> Nor <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> Martyr the ſtate of aungels, and their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towardes wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nor <hi>Auſten</hi> the true meanyng of the Pſalmes.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. 8.</note> Nor <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> of the litle prophets. Nor <hi>Ireneus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> age of Chriſt. <hi>Tertulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> knew not truth in ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Mariages. Nor <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:132003:21"/> frée will and taking of othes. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Epheſus</hi> was deceaued with <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiches</hi> hereſie. The firſt Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cell of <hi>Nice</hi> had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted a great foly but for <hi>Paphnu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tius.</hi> The third Councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> was deceaued, in forbiddyng prayers to be made vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne of God. The third Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> knewe not the truth &amp; therfore they ſet vp Images and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dles, and diſſanulled the writynges of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius. Peter Martyr</hi> ſemeth to ſome not to haue vnderſtode what <hi>Sinus Abrill</hi> ment. <hi>Beza</hi> ſaw ſome thynges that <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine</hi> ſawe not. And <hi>Mollineus</hi> would ſeme to ſée further then <hi>Beza. Muſculus</hi> confeſſeth he knoweth not that ſaying of S. Iohn, That <hi>you may be one as I and my father am one. Bucer</hi> is thought not to haue determined well of vſury. <hi>Caſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio</hi> ſayth that he vnderſtandeth not the x. part of the Apocalipſe. Mans knowledge fayleth in all thynges, <hi>Veſalius</hi> is repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by <hi>Columbus</hi> in the <hi>Anatomi. Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xius</hi> by <hi>Matheolus</hi> in the Herball. And <hi>Matheolus</hi> by others. <hi>Galene</hi> the great Phiſitian is reproued by many, <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> hath controled them all and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troled him ſelfe. In <hi>Arithmeticke</hi> they cannot hit the rule of <hi>Algebra,</hi> In <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metri
<pb facs="tcp:132003:21"/> Cardanus</hi> ſaith but <hi>Euclide</hi> hath not handled the matter with dexteritie inough. In <hi>Aſtronomy Ptolome</hi> and all his aſſiſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce are called backe by <hi>Coper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus;</hi> In Logicke they are called backe by <hi>Ramus.</hi> In morall Philoſophie, they know not what the chief good of man is, In the Gréeke toung, the phraſe of all men is controled by <hi>Dioniſius Halicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeus.</hi> In the Latine toung there is no mans ſtile, but it hath ſome blemiſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtile of <hi>Iulius Caeſar.</hi> If in toungs and Artes, where nature endoctrineth and our booke doth helpe we know not and are deceaued, then in thynges to come, the knowledge whereof is moſt hidden, it is no maruell though our fore ſight bee nought worth, if theſe eaſier thynges be ſo hard to attaine vnto, then thoſe harder thinges are moſt hardly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed and ſpecially the knowledge of thyngs to come is in truth it ſelfe a thing of great difficultie.<note place="margin">Aſtrologie.</note> And here appeareth vnto me a déepe matter, a wide contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, and a large fielde to ſpeake with or agaynſt the Aſtologers. And the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is ſomwhat doubtful. For if I ſpeake with them my text ſpeaketh agaynſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, If I ſpeake agaynſt them. The greater part of men who laugheth all learning to
<pb facs="tcp:132003:22"/> ſcorne will haue better will to be rude; &amp; leſſe loue to be learned. If I ſpeake with them <hi>Picus Mirandula</hi> ſpeaketh againſt them. If I ſpeake agaynſt them <hi>Ierony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Cardanus, Iouianus Pontanus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Marſilius Ficinus</hi> ſpeaketh with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Speakyng with them <hi>Caluine</hi> of a great iudgement ſpeaketh agaynſt me, if I ſpeake agaynſt them <hi>Phillip Melanctho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> a man of much learnyng will not ſpeake with me. And to conclude I ſay as our Sauiour Chriſt ſome tyme ſayd, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng called to bee a Iudge, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>per in matters of law about partyng of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce (he ſayd) <hi>who hath appointed me a iudge amongſt you?</hi> Chriſt would be no iudge in ſuch baſſe matters.<note place="margin">Pyuiſh ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth fooliſh iudgement.</note> But I dare not iudge in theſe learned matters, Neither will I ſeme to ouer rule the iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gements of ſuch woorthy, &amp; excellent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, yet what I miſtake I will ſay. And that I ſay, ſemeth to me to be voyde nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of reaſon, nor of conſcience. Firſt therefore I miſlike the pyu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> holynes of ſome. Who either to reſerve (as they thinke) the more power to God, do take away all the vertue, and worthyneſſe of the creatures: or els to pleaſe <hi>M. Caluin</hi> the more, do take away all <hi>Comercia coeli,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:132003:22"/> that is all the influences of heauen. But as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid <hi>Go to the beaſts of the field and they will teach thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 12.</note> So I will the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reſort, but to the contemplation of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and they cannot be ignoraunt. The herbe called <hi>Orphan</hi> liueth without any roote.<note place="margin">Naturall proffes.</note> The <hi>Mallow</hi> and the <hi>Marigold</hi> &amp; the herbe called <hi>Holitropium</hi> apply the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues to the preſence or abſence of the ſunne. The <hi>Bittell</hi> accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of the moone, commeth out and goeth in with one courſe. The <hi>Piſe myre</hi> in the full moone, worketh day &amp; night. <hi>Cucu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> in the full moone be more full, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wayning of the moone more emptie. <hi>Shel Fiſhes</hi> follow the courſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moone. The fallyng ſickenes and the ſicknes of eyes Mens ſickneſſes, and womens infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are increaſed and decreaſed by the ſemblaunce of the Moone. Yea and the great huge Sea, alſo foloweth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Moone likewiſe. This grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth alſo <hi>Caluine</hi> him ſelfe, that mellan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colly, coller, &amp; other humors are moued and wrought by the Planettes, and tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s bodyes ſomewhat more may be graunted. Howbeit, he that denyeth that the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly bodyes, haue no doings towardes, or vpon the inferiour bodyes,
<pb facs="tcp:132003:23"/> for my parte I thinke them not onely to be witles but alſo to be myndeles. But here I doe ſpecially miſlike, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologians will not onely geue out their geſſinges in generall matters. But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in particular countreys, and caſes, They will forſpeake of warre, and of peace, and of dearth, and of chepth, and as they call them, particular matters of fortune: it yrketh me farther more to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the vanitie of theſe men. For as the <hi>Saracens</hi> will ſeeme to deriue their antiquitie from <hi>Sara.</hi> And the <hi>Haggere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> from <hi>Haggar,</hi> (and that whiche would make a ſober man to laugh,<note place="margin">The Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>logers do falſely clayme an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie.</note>) The <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roldes</hi> alſo, will fetch their antiquitie of their imblaſenyng, from <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> The Papiſtes their Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from <hi>Peter:</hi> So theſe Aſtrologians will defende their fact, and proue their Arte good by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of <hi>Adam,</hi> of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iacob.</hi> As who would ſaye Aſtrologie were a thing of great primacie. We read in déede that <hi>Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> gaue very proper He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew names to foules, fiſhes, &amp; herbes. But that hee had any knowledge in the Starres that we read not.</p>
            <p>Gene .xv. It is ſayd to Abraham, <hi>Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Starres of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if thou canſt.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:132003:23"/> Auſten in his booke <hi>De Ciuitate Der.</hi> xvi. chap. ſayth thus. That <hi>thoſe are to bee contemned, which ſay they haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d out the nomber of the Starres, For it is onely the propertie of God to know the Starres &amp; their names.</hi> And ſurely if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould at any tyme haue had any knowledge in that ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; My thinke that the Patriarke <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſhould ſéeme to be inſtructed therin. For of him it is wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,<note place="margin">Cap. 24. verſ. 62.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaac went into the fieldes to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> But of the other it is not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that they went to ſtudy or dye ſtudy. Of the ſame <hi>Iſaac</hi> we doe read that hee dyd not know the day of his death, Therfore we may thus conclude. <hi>Iſaac</hi> the ſtudient did not knowe the chief parte of Aſtrologie, that is his fatall houre. Therefore <hi>Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> whiche in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture haue no name of ſtud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es dyd not ſtudy Aſtrologie, or at lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt in thoſe thynges, which the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers do challenge vnto them ſelues. I wil not vrge here the textes of <hi>Eſay</hi> or <hi>S. Auſten,</hi> or of <hi>Tertulian</hi> in his booke <hi>De habitu Mulicrum.</hi> Let them by me enioy their Arte whether it bee much; or little. νόμος, or λό<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ς, Rule or Iudgement. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I meruell, if that cleare iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:132003:24"/> may be rendred in their ſcience. Why the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do they alwayes write darkely, or falſly? darkly, like <hi>Appollo</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil of <hi>Delphos.</hi> Such a profound impoſtor, or deceauer was <hi>Noſtradamus,</hi> who gaue out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> text openly. But kept the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentary in the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cery of his own breſt. Our me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are a litle more dull they write playne, for they write playne lyes, and both halfe diſclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng, and cortallyng of their Arte, yet they pouder it with lyes ſtill. There hath ſo many gone about to tell vs great truthes, &amp; ſo few hit in litle truthes, that I ſuſpect it, there is not any truth great or litle in that their great miſtery of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie. But though they know not par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticular chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces or tymes, or moments of tymes, yet though we neuer vew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face of heauen, but poore vpon the earth like brute beaſtes, which God hath framed to looke where they like beſt. This muſt nedes be the entry doore, The threſhold, The <hi>Alpha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 8.</note> and the <hi>a. b. c.</hi> of all Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Scio quod beue erit timentibus Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. <hi>I knowe that it ſhalbe well vnto thoſe that feare God, and are afrayde of hys face. And it ſhall not bee well vnto the wicked: Neither ſhall they prolong theyr dayes, becauſe they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde
<pb facs="tcp:132003:24"/> of his face.</hi>
               </hi> Here then ſtay. And you ſhall ſée together with me. Whether it be lykely that ill, and miſchief will fall vppon the earth, the caſe is this. <q rend="margDblQuotes">If the feare of God be in men, there wil no miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief fall vppon the earth. If the feare of God be not in me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there will miſchief fall vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth.</q> And here I enter into the fearefull &amp; diſcoraging queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whether the feare of God be in this generation or not. The feare of God ye know, and the loue of God are moſt nearely knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And where ſoeuer is the loue, and feare of God there is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kéepyng of Gods commaundements. So that now I muſt demaund whether that Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes be kept on earth.<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> And now this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> groweth from bitter to bitterer, from worme woodde to gall, From worſe to worſte. For, (thought I) for me to go tell the breache of the lawes throughout the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breakers of Gods lawes, and the illnes that may, &amp; will lyght vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: Since <hi>Ionas</hi> ſo feared it, <hi>Michae</hi> ſo felt it, and <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſo ſmarted for it: (As I ſay) I tooke it be a toto cold occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, and a very vnthriftie. Sith that I my ſelfe alſo haue taſted it before with myne owne experience. And harke, how
<pb facs="tcp:132003:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> feare caſt in many extremities. This la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (thought I) is deuided into the Nobilitie, the Clergy, the Lawyers, &amp; the people. If I ſhould checke the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, I ſhould ſpeake agaynſt Lyons. If of the Lawyers,<note place="margin">Soph. iij.</note> I ſhould ſpeake agaynſt Wolfes. If of the Clergy I ſhold ſpeake agaynſt Foxes, if of the people I ſhould haue to do with Waſpes. And in déede in this reſpect I could not but compare the Nobilitie vnto Lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For as if any beaſt annointed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lyons greace, no beaſt of the foreſt will annoy hym. And as the Prouerbe ſayth, it is a greuous thyng to awake a Lyon: ſo no doubt it is both gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and ieberdous to ſpeake againſt the vices of the Nobilitie, and to wake them out of that ſléepe of ſinne, wherein they ſo ſwetly and quietly ſlomber. Though Chriſt him ſelfe called the Prieſtes and Phariſe is wolues vnder La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes ſkinnes, yet I will rather now call the Lawyers Wolues, both becauſe they are gréedy to ſwallow; and alſo in might and power ſtronger then the Clergy. The Clergy as it nowe is reſembled moſt aptly (my thought) the nature of Foxes, who thought they ſéeme to ſléepe before compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny, yet they will ſpoyle and praye when
<pb facs="tcp:132003:25"/> no body looketh on &amp; ſurely they ſleepe as ſinne is ſayd to ſléepe in Geneſis.<note place="margin">Gene. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Synne</hi> ſayth the text <hi>ſlepeth before the dores:</hi> That is ſinne ſléepeth whileſt we lyue. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we go out of the dores of this life it ſitteth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. So they will diſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble their reuengement before the eyes of the world, but when the preacher is gone out of the Pulpit, They will ſet vppon hym. The people I thought to bee lyke vnto Waſpes. For if one Waſpe ſtyng vpon a pyuiſhe affection, a nomber alſo will ſtyng for felowſhyp. So that to conclude I ſée nothyng from the worlde but emy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent daunger. And here I aſſure you I ſtode in a croſſe way, that I could not tell which path was better to treade. For diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure beyng ſo neare vnto me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world. And God beyng ſo farre of to the iudgement of fleſh &amp; bloud: I was driuen into a moſt vncerteinetie: Nor in all this world I could find any one maner thyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this caſe could reliue me, I left ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dwellers vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, &amp; lifted vp my mynde vnto hym that dwelleth in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in whoſe cauſe I did thinke once again to venter. And his ſpirit dyd aſſure me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo farre as heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is exalted aboue earth. So farre is his ſtrength exalted aboue mans ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:132003:26"/> Gods ſtrength and his mainteinaunce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mans mainteinaunce, I dyd there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the fauourable protection of God purpoſe with my ſelfe to vtter my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, How deſpiſed and odious ſoeuer it ſhould be in the eyes of the world. But becauſe I was not very certeine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it woulde better edifie this age to ſpeake in roughnes, or in myldenes of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, I thought to vſe both wayes, and kyndes. And to do as the wiſe, Lapidary doth with his pearles, who accordyng to their nature doth te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with hony. And ſome of them with vynager. So I will deale with ſome gently, and with other ſome ſharpely. Neither will I charge them with ſinne from my ſelfe: but I will aſke them of their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. And firſt to begyn with the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, I muſt nedes ſay as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid ſome tyme vnto God, <q rend="margDblQuotes">O that a man might ſpeake vnto you as hee doth vnto hys neighbour.</q> I would then demaunde of you many queſtions. And firſt I would aſke of you, whether it bee not in your Court as it was in the Court of <hi>Pharao.</hi> Where there was <hi>Princeps Piſtoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and <hi>Princeps Laniorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 11.</note> The <hi>Prince of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and the Prince of Butchers.</hi> My
<pb facs="tcp:132003:26"/> queſtion is this, whether that officers and maſters of belly cheare and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of worldly pleaſures doth grow vp to great principallitie, And rather by thoſe meanes then by wiſedome gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement, temperauncy, councell, actiuitie, Cheualry &amp;c? Agayne if I might ſpeake to you as a man doth to his neighbour, I will aſke you if all preachers bee not to you as <hi>Micheas</hi> was to the Court of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab,</hi> whileſt he pronounced victory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the <hi>Syrians,</hi> hee was a trime pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete and in great price: but at an other battell whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayd they ſhould not wyn, he was in great diſdayne.<note place="margin">3. Kyngs. 22</note> So that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng their appetites they loued him, and not ſeruyng their appetites they dyd not loue hym. Agayne I would aſke of you this queſtion, whether that you be of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> opinion in this point, who ſayth <hi>by takyng away the wicked man from the kynges preſence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouer. 29.</note> 
               <hi>his throne ſhalbe eſtabliſhed,</hi> And if ye be of that opinion whether you do practiſe, it or no? Alſo I would aſke of you whether you doe not rather delight to be noble men like vnto <hi>Eſau,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 34.</note> whoſe nobilitie was in carying foure hundred men after him, then to <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> whoſe nobilitie was in the inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:132003:27"/> of the true God, In callyng of hym, The God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> The God of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaac,</hi> The God of <hi>Iacob.</hi> Whether that ye be not like to that nobilitie whiche is ſpoken of in the fourth of <hi>Oſee.</hi> Where it is ſayd.<note place="margin">Oſee. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Their nobilitie or chief men loue bryng ye filthely?</hi> Whether ye be of the opinion of our Sauiour in the vi. of S. Iohn. <hi>Caro non prodeſt quicquam. <hi>The fleſh</hi>
               </hi> (ſayth he) <hi>profiteth nothyng.</hi> And if the fleſh profite nothyng, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you can thinke that bloud or gentry profiteth any thing? Agayn, whether that your Seruyng men do not vſe their bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as <hi>Cayne</hi> dyd hys marke. Becauſe <hi>Cayn</hi> had a marke that if any men killed him, he ſhould be puniſhed ſeuen tymes as greuouſly, But if <hi>Cayne</hi> kylled any we read in this world of no puniſhment: So I wil aſke you whether if one chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to kyll one that hath your badge, or marke hee bee ſure of execution,<note place="margin">Gene. 4.</note> or not? But if any of yours chaunce to kill one, whether that then through the priuiledge of your badge, and marke hée is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touchable, Theſe &amp; many other the lyke queſtions if I might ſpeake vnto you as to my neighbour, good Lordes and noble men, I would demaunde of you. But as
<pb facs="tcp:132003:27"/> in fleyng of an hare, or conny it is not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard to plucke of the ſkynne whileſt it come at the head, but then it is very buſie and difficulte: ſo in controlyng of vyce, it is neuer ſo hard in reformation, and ſtayeth ſo much as when it commeth to you, who are the heads, and I in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines am more likely to hurt my ſelfe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profite you. But that whiche I cannot, God can. To whom I pray for you. And to whom I commende you, and your ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous amendement. If I might ſpeake to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lawyers as vnto my neighbour, I would aſke them but this one queſtion. Whether they do not iudge <hi>Secundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that is accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward ſhew.<note place="margin">Iohn. 7.</note> Whether that the face of a noble and a meane ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a rich man &amp; a poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be all one or no? Of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clergy I wold demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, whether that in conſcience, they doe not thinke themſelues like vnto Cucumers, the whiche Cucumers, if it thunder fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen torne them ſelues round about: ſo whether that they, if there be any thun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dryng from the Court either by ſpeach, or by letter do not turne their affection &amp; that very roundly. Agayne, I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of them, whether that they doe not ſuppoſe that the worlde doth thinke
<pb facs="tcp:132003:28"/> vs very cowardly and fooliſh ſhepheards, that dare ſpeake ſo boldly agaynſt the Pope, or agaynſt ceremonies, or with ceremonies, in whiche matters we are vpholded with one faction or an other: But agaynſt vice we ſpeake nothyng, or very fayntely: And as cockes nipt with kites clawes, we cakle, but we crow not. Alſo I would aſke of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and that by their owne experience of thoſe that haue preached ſincerely, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a man preachyng frely againſt theſe two vices, vncleannes of lyfe &amp; bribery ſhould not haue hys ſoule driuen lyke a Sparrow from place to place, ſhould not haue forrowes made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ſhoulders, haue his ſoule made low vnto the duſt, &amp; be blacked with ſlaunders and aduerſity. To theſe Londonners becauſe I may ſpeake as vnto my neighbours. I will thus ſay &amp; demaunde of them. How they do liue accordyng to the profeſſion of the Goſpell, conſideryng there is ſo fewe of them good and ſo many of them naught. And agayne whether they had not rather both the preacher, and Pulpits were ſet on fire, Then they would forſake that ſwete and gaynfull ſinne of vſury. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe which haue had occaſion to try
<pb facs="tcp:132003:28"/> them haue not founde them as vnmercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as the mercyles Exchecker, as voyde of Religion as the Papiſt. I appeale to God that knoweth this, to the world that cannot for ſhame denye it. If I ſay the truth go about your owne amendement, &amp; not to hurt me. And thus much I haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gentlenes of ſpirite. If you mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile what can be ſayd more rougher I will ſpeake to you out of the <hi>5.</hi> of Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. <hi>Go, and ſearch throughout all the ſtretes of Ieruſalem, and ſee and know and enquire in euery ſtrete, whether you can finde ſuch a man, and whether there bee ſuch a one as doth iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſeeketh the truth and I will ſpare the Citie. And as truly as God li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, they will ſweare a very lye. And I ſaid, truly theſe men are poore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and they are but fooles. Becauſe they doe not know the way of Iehoua. And the Iudgement of their God. I wil go ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to the vpper ſorte and ſpeake to them for they know the Iudgement of Iehoua their God, but they alſo truly had broken the yocke, They had burſt to peeces the bandes.</hi> So that the cauſe of the deſtruction of this Citie was, that the people was not ſouthefaſt in worde,
<pb facs="tcp:132003:29"/> and the nobilitie was violent in worke: Euen ſo it is now thorough towne and countrey, There is fraude and deceate, in bargens and in all ſpeches amongeſt the people. The nobilitie or vpper ſorte are very violent, for they do not take that thyng in hand, whiche they will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch either by fauour or money, and no rich ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s matter or noble ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s matter is an ill matter, or at leaſt an vnlucky mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I may be deceaued, but if it be as I take it, and I pray God I do not miſtake it, if it be ſo, I will vtter my mynde as I am compelled: And I will ſweare an old othe ſworne oftens before by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuit Iehoua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">God lyueth &amp; by Gods lyfe is all one.</note> 
               <hi>God lyueth,</hi> or <hi>by Gods lyfe,</hi> Except you do ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d you ſhall all together periſhe. I hate no man, I ſée no man, I mynde no man: but vppon very loue, and good hart I ſpeake it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye repent ye ſhall all periſhe. O ye knowe, alas you knowe, But alas you will not know, what <hi>ill may betide vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth.</hi> But here ſome men do thinke their ſtate ſo ſure that no ill can betyde to them vpon the earth, but let vs examine this opinion. Where doeſt thou lyue? vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, what is aboue thy head? hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen. Who is the dweller in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? God.
<pb facs="tcp:132003:29"/> And thence ſayth <hi>Ieremy</hi> our ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tyed to Gods hand doth rele amayne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our neckes. God hath diuers wayes to puniſh, and diuers kyndes of puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, when as in the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 6.</note> God councelled with the Cherubins, How to puniſh the wicked people, one of the aungels ſayd thus, and an other ſayd thus. So that here by it appeareth that God hath diuers kyndes of puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Is ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hart ſo fooliſh,<note place="margin">Plagues may chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vpon the earth.</note> that it doth thinke that there can <hi>no miſchief betyde vpon the earth?</hi> There is a thing they call wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or rayne, the whiche once came ſo lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gely out of heauen that it deſtroyed well nigh euery liuyng thyng vpon the earth. But thou wilt ſay there is a raynebow, I ſay the raynebow is the worldes rayne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bow, &amp; not thy raynebow. In the rayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow it is couenaunted that the worlde ſhall not all be deſtroyed, Yet thou mayſt be deſtroyed. This <hi>euill therfore may chaunce to thee vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth.</hi> There is a thyng they call ſnow <hi>Iob</hi> calleth it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treaſures of Gods ſnowes.<note place="margin">Iob. 38.</note> God hath whole treaſures, &amp; ſtorehouſes of ſnow to deſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked. That <hi>ill alſo may be tyde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth.</hi> There is an other thyng called Hayle:<note place="margin">Exod. 9.</note> which in <hi>Egypt</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed
<pb facs="tcp:132003:30"/> all the cattell, trées, and fruites. So likewiſe in <hi>Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> the yeare of our Lord viij. hundred xxv. And though there be a Raynebow, which promiſeth ſaftie to the world from rayne, yet there is no haylebow. This therfore <hi>ill may chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vpon the earth. Blondus</hi> in his ix. booke writeth that after the death of <hi>Adeota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> there were ſo great ſtormes of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges and thunders, that it deſtroyed all thynges ſaue onely a few <hi>Pulſis</hi> and rootes. Theſe <hi>illes alſo may betide vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth.</hi> There is alſo bluſtring and fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious wyndes, whiche as <hi>Cuſpinianus</hi> writeth in the tyme of <hi>Comnenus</hi> the Emperour blew downe an huge braſen Image.<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> And in the tyme of <hi>Iob</hi> blewe down <hi>Iobs</hi> houſe &amp; his progeny. This <hi>ill alſo may betide vpon the earth.</hi> There is alſo the ayre it ſelfe which may engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der frogges to trouble thée, as in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and Graſhoppers as in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talie,</hi> and as <hi>Cromerus</hi> reporteth in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lonia</hi> the yeare of our Lorde. <hi>1473.</hi> This ayre if it be very whote may bring the plagues of peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and of the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynges ſicknes, wherewith we are well acquaynted, if it be very cold it may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all the foules of the ayre, as ſome
<pb facs="tcp:132003:30"/> times in the dayes of the Emperour <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinian,</hi> it may frees the Sea and kill fiſhes as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas,</hi> which is teſtified by <hi>Nicephorus</hi> &amp; <hi>Paulus Diaconus.</hi> Theſe <hi>illes alſo may betide vpon the earth.</hi> There is alſo an other thyng moſt dredfull and viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led fire. And though all other plagues fayle, that plague wilt not faile <hi>Mallachi</hi> iiij. it is ſayd that <hi>the day of Iudgement will burne like an ouen.</hi> Eſay lxvj. it is ſayd <hi>Behold the day of the Lord ſhalbe in fire.</hi> The fires y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be in your Cities you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> helpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with cla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pes &amp; buckettes,<note place="margin">The great daungers many ways hangyng o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our heades.</note> if it be wilde fire you can que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch it with milke &amp; vinager. But this fire as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſayth <hi>ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not bee quenched,</hi> It is ſayd in Luke xvij. That <hi>in the dayes of the ſonne of man it ſhalbe as in the dayes of Noe.</hi> In the dayes of <hi>Noe</hi> a litle doue could not ſet her foote on the grounde for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daunce of water. In the dayes of the ſonne of man a litle doue ſhall not ſette downe her foote, but it ſhalbe ſinged with fire. This euill wilbe a generall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and this <hi>euill ſhal betyde vpon the earth.</hi> But let me come neare vnto thée, And demaunde a freſh of thée. Doeſt thou beleue that no miſchief can betyde vpon
<pb facs="tcp:132003:31"/> the earth? vppon what part of the earth doeſt thou dwell? In an Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Thou muſt remember the Iſles called <hi>Maiorica</hi> and <hi>Minorica</hi> were deſtroyed with connyes. As alſo the Iſle <hi>Anaphe,</hi> as <hi>Euſtachius</hi> writeth, if it be an Iland, the ſea may eate it vp, as it hath done diuers Ilandes. There is alſo great daunger by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the place of the arriuall of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. This <hi>ill alſo may betyde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this kynde of earth.</hi> But what profeſſion is thy Iland of? Of a Chriſtian profeſſion. Therefore the Turke is the great and ſworne enemy. What is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turke. One that hath moſt large and wyde Signio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, one that vſeth ſeuere diſcipline and policie, One that wynneth much, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth litle: One y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath a good affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes, and this laſt yeare hath wonne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fine &amp; wealthy Iland of <hi>Cyprus.</hi> And no dout is ſet on by God to go forward. The Turke they wil ſay is farre of. But God whiſtelleth to thoſe that are farre of that they come lyke bees, to light where hee wil haue them. Thou laugheſt at me per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture to ſée me ſo carefull. I morne for thée without peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture to ſée thée ſo careles. Thou laugheſt at me, and God at thée. Thou careſt not, but care, thou
<pb facs="tcp:132003:31"/> laugheſt but wéepe. And do good whileſt thou mayſt thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not tell what <hi>ill will betyde vpon the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the name of the Iland? Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: what neighbours haſt thou? <hi>Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> and <hi>Flaunders.</hi> The one thou canſt not reteyne in frendſhyp but as men. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is thyne enemy moſt ſubtill, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, willyng and able to doe the hurt. Do good therfore to all men, and caſt thy bread vppon the face of the water, For thou canſt not tell what <hi>ill will betyde vpon the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is England an whole Iland? No, but halfe an Iland, how is the other halfe, Scotland affected. Some well, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ill, as you haue vnderſtanded. They haue bene oftens in minde to put out the candle of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. To take away our <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> the breath of our noſtrels, and to ſet vp hipocrites vpon vs. O Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, what if thou be ſodenly ouer taken as the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man with her child panges? Then wilt thou wiſh that thou haddeſt bene mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp; delt thy bread. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſhalt ſée, &amp; féele what <hi>ill wil betyde vpon the face of the earth.</hi> But beyng but halfe an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, art thou firme and truſtie within thy ſelfe? Nay, art not thou a ſnacke with
<pb facs="tcp:132003:32"/> young thyne owne broode beyng ready to bight out thy belly? Englande hath ſwordes drawen out agaynſt her, but pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uideth no buckler. The ſtate of England is lyke to children ſittyng rechleſſe in the Market ſtede. We playe, and pype to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but they relent not: our Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are like vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> muſike which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeaketh of.<note place="margin">Ethic. 1.</note> Which when it is once done there is no more remembraunce of it. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue Lawyers in law matters and folow them, Phiſitians and follow them: Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors and follow them, they here prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers but they do not follow them. I am very ſory, for I doe verely thinke that ſome <hi>ill wil betyde vpon this earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But admitte thou feare no generall puniſhmentes by warres, by plagues, by famine: Yet much <hi>ill may fall vpon the earth.</hi> What particular ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> art thou but ſome <hi>ill may chaunce to thee vpon the earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Il may hap to euery man.</note> Art thou a Magiſtrate? if thou be a good one thou mayſt be toſt &amp; wrong like <hi>Dauid:</hi> If thou bee an ill one, thou mayeſt breake thy necke like <hi>Hely.</hi> If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be a noble ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou mayſt be ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly dabte to the hart with a dagger like <hi>Abner</hi> or lyke <hi>Amaſias.</hi> If y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be an old Courtier thou mayſt be put to death,<note place="margin">2. Kings. 20</note> at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng
<pb facs="tcp:132003:32"/> in of a new kyng like <hi>Ioab.</hi> If thou lackeſt example read the bookes of the kynges what hath chaunced vnto kings. Truth it is, &amp; tyme doth tell that kynges the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, and Courtiers of great eſtate haue their floriſhyng, and their fallyng, their <hi>Regno,</hi> and their <hi>Regnaui,</hi> their <hi>Surſum,</hi> and their <hi>Deorſum.</hi> Let them ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore breake their bread and liue well for they know not what ill wil betyde vppon the earth: If thou be a Miniſter and a good Miniſter, then thou ſhalt alwayes be oppreſſed in the world, if thou be an ill Miniſter thou mayſt bee deſtroyed for thyne Idolatry as <hi>Helias</hi> the Prophete deſtroyed <hi>Balles</hi> Prieſtes. If thou bee a graſer of cattaile, thou mayſt be ſtayne of thyne owne brother like <hi>Abell.</hi> If thou bee a ploughman thou mayſt chaunce to kill an other like vnto <hi>Cayn.</hi> If thou be a landed man, thou mayſt be ſpoyled lyke <hi>Naboth:</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Kyngs. 21</note> either by violence of Courty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, either by ſubtiltie of Lawyers. No trade nor eſtate through the whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth hath any charter of ſafty. <q rend="margDblQuotes">Caſt thy bread therfore vppon the waters, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide it, and part it, for thou canſt not tell what wil betyde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth:</q> for both thy ſelfe art ſubiect vnto euils, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:132003:33"/> thy goodes are ſubiect vnto euilles. For what haſt thou which is not ſubiect vnto caſualtie? Haſt thou gemmes, iewels, and pearles? Théeues may burſt in, &amp; ſteale them. Haſt thou gold, ſiluer, coyne, plate, and mettals? Ruſt may freate them, or théeues may ſteale them. Haſt thou tape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, ſilkes, clothes, wardropes, mothes may eate them? and of them ſelues they will waxe old. Haſt thou great ſtockes of ſhéepe, they may bee burnt from heauen as <hi>Iobs</hi> were. Haſt thou oxen, cattell, horſe? enemyes may take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away. Haſt thou houſes, and fayre manſion places? They may be burnt with fire like to <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> or they may be blowne downe like to <hi>Iobes</hi> houſes? Haſt thou graſſe &amp; corne? it may bee as in the dayes of the Prophet Helias.<note place="margin">3. Kings. 17</note> 
               <hi>The heauens will not heare the earth. And the ſoyle ſhalbe barren, for lacke of rayne and moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture.</hi> Whileſt thou haſt light and tyme woorke that whiche is good. Breake thy bread and caſt it vpon the waters, thou knoweſt not who ſhall enioy it. For thou "knoweſt not what wilbe tyde vppon the earth: For as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Mulbery tree doth budde, it ſheweth the ſpring to be at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, as the commyng of the ſwallowes is an
<pb facs="tcp:132003:33"/> argument of Sommer, lightenynges of thunder, ſmocke of fire, bright ſkye of fayre weather, Prickyng in the left ſyde of plureſies, Suddenly thernes of ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and rutlyng in the throate of death: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo, &amp; more then ſo I gather, &amp; ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſe, that ſome <hi>ill wil hap vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the face of the earth.</hi> Trée may budde and yet no ſpring come, Swallowes may flye and yet no Sommer come, Smocke may be and yet no fire, voluntary lythernes &amp; yet no ſickenes, Prickyng in the left ſide and yet no plureſie: But where there is ſo much ſinne, and ſo ſmall repentaunce, Gods mercy ſo abuſed and his iuſtice ſo egged on, There muſt nedes ſome <hi>ill be tyde vpon the earth.</hi> You will ſay you know not, I thinke, ſo but the more is your ſhame, the greater is your Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: you know, not ſay you? lie for ſhame ſay not ſo,<note place="margin">Forewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges of miſchief.</note> Paules ſtéeple long ago gaue you light inough to knowe by burnyng. The Thamis and other waters might haue taught you by their extraordinary flowyng. The Starres by their blaſing, mountaines by mouyng, Thine owne people by rebellyng. Theſe thynges ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue that thou ſhalt be ſicke, and diſeaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Agayn, I will reaſon with thée as S.
<pb facs="tcp:132003:34"/> Paule doth in prouyng the reſurrection. <hi>If</hi> (ſayth S. Paul) <hi>that the reſurrection bee not, then all our preachyng is in vayne.</hi> So may I ſay of theſe tymes we haue all ioyned together, All y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachers of this land haue ſéene miſchief hangyng ouer thy head, Either all our preachyng &amp; foreſeyng is to no purpoſe or els ſome miſchief wil betyde vpon the earth. But thou wilt ſay, thou knoweſt it not, Alas, therefore poore blynd countrey, for thou wilt not ſee, deafe countrey for thou wilt not heare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eedles, for thou w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t not féele, If thy preachers would goe lyke <hi>Eſay</hi> in ſacke cloth, like <hi>Ieremy,</hi> with yro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s about their necke, if they would deuide theyr clockes lyke as the Prophet did to <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kings. 11</note> yet I would haue no hope of thy recouery. Thou art like <hi>Eſau</hi> who now hauyng loſt his patrimony did ſit downe eate, drinke, and was mery. Thou art like the Iewes whom <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh of xxviij. chap.<note place="margin">Examples of depe ſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie.</note> Who cryed out, That <hi>they had ſmitte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truce with death, &amp; made a couenant with their graue.</hi> Sodome would not know that the vengeaunce of God come vpon it, and therfore early in the mornyng fire, and brimſtone rayned vpon them, and they were deſtroyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:132003:34"/> they could well open their eyes to ſée the maner of their deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The people of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople</hi> was ſo quyet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the town was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that their enemyes beyng preſente and their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murs broken, they woulde geue nothing to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> réedifiyng therof. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, his Captaines, and people were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and murthered. The Empreſſe and her Gentlewomen were abuſed. The Empire for euer was remoued from the eaſt. This was before foretold her by her Prophetes, but <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> would not ſée it. When the Duke of <hi>Bourbon</hi> ſacked Rome, and the campe did now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uirone the whole towne, the Pope, and hys Cardinals were ſo quyet, that beyng at Maſſe there were ſome of them take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their goodes ſpoyled, &amp; them ſelues moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, &amp; derided in moſt vilanous maner. <hi>Caſſandra</hi> cried out that the horſe which was in <hi>Troye</hi> would deſtroy <hi>Troye,</hi> yet the blynde <hi>Troyans</hi> would not heare it, nor ſée it, They heard harneſſed men clincke in the horſe belly, but they would not marke it. Harneſt men in an horſes belly deſtroyed <hi>Troye:</hi> And harneſſed me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a Lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s belly wil they not deſtroy En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland? The horſe they ſayd was ſo holy
<pb facs="tcp:132003:35"/> that it might not be deſtroyed, and yet the holy horſe deſtroyed the Citie, it yrketh me except you take hede to your ſelues to forthinke your miſeries. <hi>Caſſandra</hi> rent her heare vpon the deſtruction of Troy. <hi>Ieremy</hi> wiſhed for eeſternes of teares to wéepe the ſinnes of his people.<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.</note> Chriſte wept vppon <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 19.</note> we may with teares of bloud be ſory, and morne for the ſtormes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will rage in this natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If they will not be warned, watch, watche, faſt, faſt, pray, pray, caſt your bread geue your bread, breake your bread, for you know not what <hi>ill will betyde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the cloudes be full, they will poure out their rayne vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, the cloudes hauyng much rayne they let it fall. The trées hauyng fruites,<note place="margin">An other reaſon to be liberall.</note> they let them drop. The fountaines hauyng waters they let them runne. The cattell hauyng milke they let it ſtreme. The ſhepe hauing woll they yeld it. The foules hauyng fethers they caſt them. By theſe naturall exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples mans nature is exhorted to bee liberall. The cloudes if they be full they yeld forth their rayne, if the cloudes reteyne their owne fulnes it is a burthen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloudes to reteine it.<note place="margin">Much ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are burthens.</note> Much rayne is a burthen to clouds, &amp; much riches are burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Abraham</hi> is ſayd in xiij. of Geneſis to be
<pb facs="tcp:132003:35"/> burthened with golde. <hi>Abraham</hi> was a good man, and yet it burthened hys head to bee buſie with the care of his gold. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, to be puft vp in pride and vayne earthly cogitations is a burthen to the ſoule, but that is the effect of much riches as doth appeare in the firſt of Timothy the vj. chap. Therfore to be very riche is a burthen. Agayne to eate much, drinke much, and reſt much is a burthen vnto the ſoule, though it bee pleaſaunt to the body. But in the xij. of Luke it is proued that aboundaunce of riches maketh one to eate much, drinke much, &amp; reſt much: Therfore as much rayne is a burthen to cloudes: So much riches are burthens to men. Agayne, that whiche doth plucke a mans hart into diuers thoughtes and cogitations, that is a burthen vnto men. But in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vj. of Mathew, it is ſayd <hi>where thy treaſure is, there is thy hart:</hi> So that if a mans treaſure be in an hundred places, his hart is in as many places ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to be very riche is a very great bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Agayne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which maketh a man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for the kyngdome of heauen is a great burthen vnto a mans ſoule. But much riches maketh a man as vnapte to go to heauen as a camell to créepe thorough a
<pb facs="tcp:132003:36"/> nedels eyes. Therefore aboundaunce of riches is a burthen vnto man. Agayne, that whiche maketh a man to depart vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willyngly out of his life is a burthen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mans ſoule, but that doe great riches. As doth appeare Sirach xli. <hi>O death howe bitter is thy memory vnto hym that doth lyue quietly. &amp;c.</hi> Therefore plenty of riches is a burthen vnto mans ſoule. A litle will ſerue nature. Much riches doth in our lyfe tyme diſeaſe vs. And will at our death trouble vs. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloudes poure out their rayne let vs bee frée and diſpence them. Much riches made <hi>Ezechias</hi> lay his hart to the.<note place="margin">Eſay. 39.</note> Much riches vndid <hi>Salomon,</hi> and vndid the Church of Rome, and in all degrees &amp; ſtates are very peſtiferous. In the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie they haue this effect, They worke appetite without meaſure, and as a drop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the more he drinketh, the more he may: ſo theſe men as it is in the <hi>5.</hi> of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> ioyne houſe to houſe, and lande to lande: euen ſo farre as there is no more ground to purchaſe. In corrupt ſpirituall and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall officers, this aboundaunce of money worketh all maner of miſchief. <hi>Saluſt,</hi> ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a kyngdome is eaſly preſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meanes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which it is gotten.
<pb facs="tcp:132003:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> Theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome to take good héede to that ſaying of <hi>Saluſt,</hi> for they get their roomes with money, and mainteine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. The ſtrength of the <hi>Eliphante</hi> is in hys ſnoute, Of the Bore in his tuſke, of the Lyon in his pawes of the Dogge in his iawes, of the Horſe in his hofe, of the Bull in his hornes, of the Hare in her féete, of the Vrchen in his prickes, of the Cocke in his ſpurres, of the Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke in her tallentes, and of theſe Magiſtrats in their money.<note place="margin">The loue of money corruptetly the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth.</note> This money is their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for all their ſinnes, the Monarche of the world, the maſter of miſrule, the abater of diſcipline, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmother of wrinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led countenaunces. The wynges whiche they flye with, the legges that they ſtand vpon, the ſtaffe that they leane vpon, the buckler that heareth of, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword that ſtricketh, their glory, and their God that holdeth vp their head. Though a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſinnes, &amp; enormities co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe them on the right hand, And ten thouſand on the left hand, yet vnder the patronage of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney they will lay them downe, and ſlepe quyetly. I had rather if I were rich bring ten Riuers from Ware to London, build vp ten new Exchanges, build vp Paules ſteple many tymes, them onely to defray
<pb facs="tcp:132003:37"/> ſuch ſommes of money as are ſwallowed vp in this Realme by the way of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. O that Magiſtrates, and Miniſters ſhould euidently in the ſight of the world redeme their ſinnes with money. O that money ſo baſſe, and earthly a thing ſhuld preſerue wickednes, and conquere hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, wryng, and vndoe godly preachers, confound learning, ſuppreſſe godlyneſſe, hurt heauen, and do iniury to God hym ſelfe. How much better were it for theſe men if they be full to do like the cloudes, to gowſh, and drope out where it nedeth "and to caſt their almes vppon the face of the earth? Alſo to the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple aboundaunce of riches is a great bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Gregory Nazienzen</hi> ſayth that <hi>a great belly ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not enter in at a narrow gate.</hi> But theſe men hauing aboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of riches do ſtroute out their bellyes with eating, and drinkyng. Therfore riches is a burthen vnto them. Agayne, it is repor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of <hi>Naball,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kings. 25</note> that when his wife had ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen ſome of his goods to <hi>Dauid</hi> his hart was as heauy as a ſtone: So likewiſe in theſe Londonners the grief of geuyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and the feare of loſing, maketh them ſome tymes heauyer to bee weyed in a payre of ballaunce, their couetous hart
<pb facs="tcp:132003:37"/> and wretched humor maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clud it maketh ſadnes.<note place="margin">Marke. 10.</note> For the you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g man that was very rich <hi>went ſade away</hi> ſayth the Scripture: Agayne it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth quarelling, and brabling, as betwixt <hi>Lot</hi> and <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 12.</note> And the two brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in S. Luke, whiche ſtroue about inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunces. And commonly in this world, it maketh great garboiles. And when as they them ſelues will not beſtow it vpon the poore or to good vſe, Then the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place will ſucke it vp. The Kinges bench will ſuppe it vp, and the Chauncery will ſwallow it vp. Therfore do like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloudes which drope vpon the dry ground. Geue accordyng to the neceſſitie of thoſe that want,<note place="margin">The cloudes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow the rayne wher it nedeth.</note> be plentyfull vnto thy poore and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the example of the liberall cloudes which let their waters guſhe vppon the face of the earth. And if there might be reaſon in an vnreaſonable thyng, me thinke theſe cloudes might moue vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to liberalitie. For how reaſonable is this in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloudes that they beſtow their rayne where it needeth that is vppon the drye earth. Where it needeth the cloudes are liberall. And where it nedeth not I wold not haue you liberall. As for example you beſtow vpon your bellyes vj. vij. or ten
<pb facs="tcp:132003:38"/> diſhes, your bellyes are filled with much fewer, your bellyes therfore nede it not. You haue for your backes chaunge of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, fewtes many and coſtely: The poore haue none, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre is their peticotte, and they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed with cold, as with a garment, your backes neede it not, the poore nede it. You haue huge quantitie of clothes, and ſilkes aboute your loynes, they haue ſcarce <hi>Ieremyes</hi> lynnen brée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches aboute their loynes,<note place="margin">Ierem. 13.</note> your loynes neede it not, their loynes neede it. You haue proude and rich chaines about your neckes, I doubt in this caſe obſeruyng true charitie howe you can doe it. Your neckes nede it not. They dye for extreme miſerie therfore they nede it. Ye Ladies, and Gentilwomen ye woare farthingals about your legges, your legges are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from the cold warmely inough fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, The legges of the poore are vnclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed: yours are to much clothed: your legges nede it not, theirs nede it. Ye La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes and Gentilwomen ye are women, and but women, S. Paule willeth you not ſo decke your ſelues with gold. But you, you decke your ſelues, you pricke your ſelues, you pruen your ſelues, you ſpangle your ſelues, you pouder your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.
<pb facs="tcp:132003:38"/> And being but earthen Ladies you, would make your ſelues golden Ladyes. Beleue me Ladyes you nede it not, The poore dyeth for it, therfore they neede it. Alſo touching your fethers<note place="margin">Fethers.</note> what ſay you to fethers? You ſay ye do &amp; wil weare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I thinke ſo, for I ſée it in dede, ye weare them greate, huge, monſtrous, redde, white, blacke, blew, raynebow colerd, partie colerd, and in all kynde of coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. The world ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> witneſſe you weare them, and yet me thinketh you nede the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. For, if the weather bée whote they helpe you not with ſhaddowe, if it bee extreme cold they warme you not with heate: if your heare fall of, they are not comfortatiue, If your brayne panne pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh they are not reſtrictiue, nor if your brayne periſhe they are not reſtoratiue. Truely accordyng to my iudgement I thinke your heades nede them not, The poore dyeth for want, therfore the poore nede them. Agayne diuers richmen hang great huge walles with Tapiſtrie, and their galleryes with chargeable, and coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pictures, and pile great heapes of plate vppon their tables. I ſay not but theſe thynges may be ſuffered, but that in ſo great exceſſe of ſome men, that ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:132003:39"/> men ſhould dye for want that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable.<note place="margin">An other reaſon to liberalitie.</note> Beſtow it not therfore vppon your walles, &amp; tables, which nede it not, but poure it out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore which nede it. Now agayne here followeth an other argument to perſuade vs to liberalitie, which is to be drawen likewiſe out of the former wordes, which ſay that the clouds rayne vppon the earth. So that the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument is this. The cloudes whiche dyd aſcende from the earth do by all meanes they can benefite the earth. So we that haue our begynnyng from God muſt by all meanes we can employ all our benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence towardes God. But benefite God we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not, nor we nede not, for the earth is his, and the fulnes thereof, But if we helpe the poore, we helpe him, if we féede the poore, we féede him, viſite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite him, cloth them, we cloth him, if we poure out vpon them, we poure out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, ſo we ſhall ſupply their neceſſitie, &amp; faithfully, and truly fulfill our own duty.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">The text.</note>The tree where it falles, whether it bee towardes the North, or towardes the South, there it lyeth.</q>
            <p>If this text be expounded as it is commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:132003:39"/> then this argument riſeth vpon it. It thou dye thou muſt lye like a rotten trée, and beare no fruite.</p>
            <p>But thou muſt dye:</p>
            <p>Therfore thou muſt lye &amp; beare no frut,<note place="margin">An other reaſon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuadyng to liberalitie.</note> nor geue almes, when thou art dead.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Maior</hi> or greater propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may be thus enlarged. The fall of man is like the fall of a trée. So it is ſayd in xxv. Gene. That <hi>Iſmaell dyd fall before hys bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> A trée beyng falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beareth no frute. Graſſe beyng fallen beareth no flower: nor a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beyng falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; dead ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not worke. Therfore it is ſaid Eccle. ix. <hi>The dead do not knowe any thyng, nor there is not any farther reward for them.</hi> So that here is taken away either doing, or ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng in an other world, in the way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of purgyng. Neither is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Purgatory, but onely the bloud of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which doth purge vs from all our ſinnes. <hi>Tyndall,</hi> and <hi>Frith,</hi> and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Curio</hi> haue diſcredited that matter. Maſter <hi>Hardings</hi> loude voyce hath helpt to ryng down the paynes of Purgatory. And <hi>Verone</hi> hath hunted Purgatory vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death. And as S. Iames ſayth to rich men in his <hi>5.</hi> chap. <hi>Goe to you rich me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and houle. Becauſe your riches are
<pb facs="tcp:132003:40"/> rotten:</hi> So it may be ſayd, houle you he Monkes, and you ſhe Monkes, and all you farmers of the prouince of Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note place="margin">Apocal. 18.</note> it is fallen, it is fallen. Her marchants may houle, and morne for thoſe thynges that were dearely ſold, and for precious value, are now not worth any thyng, all her fatte thynges and notable thyngs are gone and can be found no more. Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory is chaſed to the death, there is no Purgatory after this lyfe. There is no doyng of good nor ſufferyng of ill by the way of clenſing, &amp; therfore <hi>Salomon</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth a liuing dog, &amp; a dead Lyon toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; preferreth the liuing dog, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead Lyon, becauſe the dogge ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do ſome thyng,<note place="margin">Eccl. 9.</note> &amp; the Lyon nothyng. At our death commeth our <hi>conſummatum eſt.</hi> There is a full pauſe and a periode that we can woorke no farther, therefore the riche man beyng in hell, could neither helpe him ſelfe nor his frendes. And therefore beare frutes and yelde frutes whileſt ye ſtande, for bee you ſure that the dayes will come on that you muſt fall, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come both lyueleſſe, and fruteleſſe, You muſt dye bee you well aſſured. Doe you not ſée how cloudes vaniſhe away trées fall downe, and graſſe vadeth: ſo lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe you muſt periſh. Marke alſo what ſ.
<pb facs="tcp:132003:40"/> Iohn ſayth. <hi>The world paſſeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Epiſt. 2.</note> but you are a parcel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, therfore you muſt paſſe and periſhe likewiſe. The long ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Mathuſala</hi> had an end, therefore your ſhort lyues muſt haue an end. It is ſaid that <hi>Adam</hi> liued and dyed, <hi>Noe</hi> lyued and dyed, <hi>Iacob</hi> lyued and dyed, So that death and dying is the kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the ſong. Now theſe two pointes doe appeare both that we muſt dye, and alſo when we are dead, that we ſhalbe fruteleſſe, and vnprofitable. Let vs doe good whileſt we can, for the dayes will come that we ſhall not be able.</p>
            <p>And though this expoſition doth pleaſe ſome, and yeldeth conuenient matter for this purpoſe, yet me thinketh it may be expounded more fittly, and ſenſibly to the meanyng of <hi>Salomon,</hi> and that is thus.</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">The text.</note>If the fruite of the tree fall into the North, or the South, there they are.</q>
            <p>That is, there are ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders by together vp the fruite, &amp; this expoſition may be as well iuſtified by the Hebrew toungue as the other. And ſerueth the authours drift very aptly, as though he ſhould thus ſay,
<pb facs="tcp:132003:41"/> Cloudes yeld rayne, and trées geue their fruite. Trées paſſe not whether it bee to the North, or to the South. But where ſo euer men will reſorte together them, There they will let fall of all ſides vnto all men. Thus cloudes and trées are pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of freneſſe, and mirrors of libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. And thus much ſéemeth <hi>Salomon</hi> to ſay in theſe latter wordes where he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of trées. Where in I note theſe iij. thynges,<note place="margin">Note.</note> the one that he vſeth eloquence in perſuadyng to almes, the other that he likeneth as it were the ſight and ſhew of the world to an apple trée about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which men runne for fruite, and the laſt that he proueth liberalitie out of theſe naturall ſcholes as out of cloudes and trées.</p>
            <p>And firſt concernyng the eloquence of <hi>Salomon</hi> it is noted in this place by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before me. And therefore I am the bolder out of this particular place to ryſe vp to a generall, and ſpeake ſome thyng of eloquence. And but that I looke to haue better occaſion here after to write ſome full treatiſe of the eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of preachers, I would nowe haue vſed both order, and more ſpéech to the handlyng of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And firſt touching that obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they haue out of S. Paule, ſpeakyng of
<pb facs="tcp:132003:41"/> the perſuaſible woordes of mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Me thinketh that ſpéech of S. Paul ſhould be no preiudice to eloquence. For he ſpeaketh of thoſe that goe about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue by ſuch kynde of ſpéech. Otherwiſe in perſuadyng to Religion S. Paul hath vſed rhetoricall woordes of mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.</note> and alſo reaſons of mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. So he proueth that the holy Ghoſt cannot bee remoued by the nature of a pawne or pledge, he proueth likewiſe the reſurrection by corne caſt into the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: Therfore neither this ſaying of S. Paul, Nor any ſaying or doyng of hys that I know can be agaynſt eloquence. So that it be vſed as it ſhould be and be ſuch elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as it ſhould be. Touchyng that which <hi>S. Ierome</hi> telleth of him ſelfe, that he was cited before the tribunall ſeate of God, for to much reading and delighting in <hi>Tullies</hi> eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I force not whether it were ſo, or it were not ſo. For as the old ſaying is, where the Philoſopher lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, there the Phiſitian begynneth: So I ſay where <hi>Tullyes</hi> eloquence endeth and ceaſeth, there the eloquence of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie begynneth: And therefore I would put a great difference betwene <hi>Tullyes</hi> eloquence, parliament eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie
<pb facs="tcp:132003:42"/> eloquence. And truly our ſpéeches ſhall as much differ from theirs, as the ſpirite doth from the mynde, and almoſt as heauen doth from the worlde, ſo much differre this and that kynde of eloquence. I doe not wreake down as intollerable, neither doe I thinke it all together ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, to perſuade with a common world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly phraſe, and with an humaine kynde of Rhetoricke. But the wordes of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are holy, and heauenly, &amp; wil worke greater,<note place="margin">Diuine elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</note> and more déeper impreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and the eloquence of Scripture is as fitt for holynes, as the wordes of <hi>Homere</hi> be fit for warre, or the woordes of <hi>Cicero</hi> for peace, or the woordes of <hi>Catullus</hi> for wantonnes. And truly for diuinitie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters we haue eloquence inough to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the ſcriptures. And it were no hard matter (but that I deferre it to ſome other treatiſe) to ſhewe by a large diſcourſe the great plenty of figures, and eloquent ſpéeches that are to be found in the Scriptures. So <hi>Eſay</hi> vſeth the figure of <hi>Paronomazia,</hi> when hee ſayth <hi>Sorim Sorerim,</hi> as though a man would ſay, carnall Cardinals, fleſhly Friers. Again, in the xxiiij.<note place="margin">Eſay. 24.</note> chapter he vſeth theſe wordes <hi>Paecath, Pacad, Pac.</hi> As though I ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:132003:42"/> ſpeake in our Engliſhe phraſe <hi>Darthe, Daunger, Death.</hi> So likewiſe he ſayth in an other place: I looked for <hi>Miſhpar</hi> and behold <hi>Miſhpa,</hi> whiche is as this, I thought hee would haue healt me, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold he beate me.<note place="margin">Ierem La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 2.</note> The Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> vſeth the figure <hi>Anaphora</hi> in begynning certeine Verſes, with one letter in hys lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. It is written that old father <hi>Iacob</hi> made his teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Verſis. And <hi>S. Ierome</hi> and <hi>Arator</hi> do write, that <hi>Iob</hi> in the Hebrew toung did write <hi>Hexame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter verſes.</hi> Dauid vſeth he figure of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phonema,</hi> when he endeth thus, <hi>bleſſed is euery one that truſteth in him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 2.</note> Paul vſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure of exclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayth thus. <hi>Wretched man that I am who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death.</hi> Iob vſeth the figure of wiſhyng when he ſayth.<note place="margin">Iob. 6.</note> 
               <hi>O that my ſinnes were wayd in a payre of ſcoales.</hi> S. Paule v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the figure of <hi>Antiſtaſis</hi> when he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth theſe woordes together απορουμενος εκπορουμενοι.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> As though a man ſhould ſay Courtiers, Carters, Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſis, Mattockes, Kynges, Caytif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of <hi>Reticentia,</hi> as thus, <hi>Sonnes of men how long my glory vnto ſhame?</hi> He meaneth, how long will you ſtudy to
<pb facs="tcp:132003:43"/> bryng my glory vnto ſhame?<note place="margin">Actes. 23.</note> 
               <hi>S. Paul</hi> vſeth the figure of <hi>Sarcaſmos</hi> or tauntyng, as when he ſayth I knew not he was a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate,<note place="margin">3. Kings. 24</note> ſo doth the Prophet <hi>Micha</hi> ſay <hi>Go vp ye ſhall wynne</hi> hee meaneth they ſhall not wynne. So y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prophet <hi>Hely</hi> bid the Prieſtes cry hygher,<note place="margin">1. Kings. 18</note> when in déede he ieſted at them, and thought it was to no purpoſe at all for them to cry. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, the Scripture is ful of figures, and eloquent ſpeches, as when the Prophet <hi>Ezechiell</hi> will deſcribe an obſequious Clergie, hee ſayth they put cuſhynes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the elbowes of Magiſtrates. To be obſtinate, the Scripture calleth to be of an hard necke. To be impudent, it calleth a brothels brow. A ſowthyng page it cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a geuer of titles. An eloquent man it calleth a perſonage of ſpéeches, a bablyng hipocrite it calleth a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lippes. To liue ſorrowfully it calleth to eate the bread of ſorrow. To lyue ioyfully it calleth to liue the dayes of heauen. If any man be wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, the Scripture will ſay that hée may waſhe his wayes with butter, And that oyle doth drop out of his rockes. To be low brought the ſcripture calleth to haue hys ſoule cleane to the duſt. But theſe thynges are infinite, and will rather
<pb facs="tcp:132003:43"/> beſéeme a great Diuinitie dictionary, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a péece of a ſmall Sermon. <hi>Salomon</hi> him ſelfe in the xij. of Eccle. ſayth, <hi>that he ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed to ſearch out pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wordes, &amp; to handle his matters handſomly.</hi> And he that wil ſée in déede what eloquence is to be founde in Scripture, let hym read <hi>Caſtalio</hi> in his preface to the <hi>5.</hi> bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Strigelius</hi> in his preface to the Pſalmes. Nay let hym perfectly and with iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, read the workes of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> of <hi>Iob,</hi> of <hi>Dauid,</hi> of <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> of <hi>Eſay</hi> of <hi>Michae.</hi> And, I thinke he wil no more hereafter be an aduerſary to eloquence, For, by the faythful, and cloſe imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe men is gotten a true, &amp; godly kynde of eloquence. And, thus much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernyng the gift of eloquence that it be not deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in preachers, as alſo that preachers do not vſe a vayne, &amp; frothy kinde of elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as alſo that you good hearers will at this tyme ſuffer your ſelues to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the eloquent words of <hi>Salomon,</hi> who exhorteth you by the example of cloudes, and trées to be liberall.</p>
            <p>And now to the <hi>2.</hi> point whiche ſayth where the apples fal there they are: And, here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter falleth out ſo fitly that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not but compare the great buſines dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges
<pb facs="tcp:132003:44"/> and ſtruglyngs in this world, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a company of all kynde of people wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng about an apple trée, lepyng, &amp; ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng about it for apples. Whereſoeuer apples fal, there they ſnatch, &amp; there they are. And wherſoeuer any litle commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie falleth out in the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weale, there ſwarmeth together whole legions to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of worldlynges,<note place="margin">The world like an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple tree.</note> there they are. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it blamefull that men ſhould go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their owne commodities, But that they be two buſie and to dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And that often tymes they beate the trée to much, to ſoone, &amp; to many wayes. Neither care they whoſe the trée is, or whoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apples bee, or whence they droppe, ſo that they may ouertake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the apples of the mouth, young and fooliſh boyes will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture all haſſardes, for the apples of the eyes and the apples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purſe, this whole fooliſhe age of ours is moſt aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous. Where aduauntage is there they are. If there be aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage in corruptyng of the holy Bible, there they are. And therfore in the common tranſlation, they haue ſo corrupted it. It was profitable, that ſome thyng ſhould be writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the fragments of Chriſtes body, and therfore they haue deuiſed that
<pb facs="tcp:132003:44"/> 
               <hi>Clement</hi> ſhould write ſuche a treatiſe. Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keries &amp; Abbeyes were profitable, &amp; therfore they haue brought to paſſe, that <hi>Dioniſius Ariopagita</hi> ſhoulde ſpeake of mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes in his dayes. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clud, they haue ſought out profite vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> in certaine Epiſtles. And vnder the name of <hi>Gayus</hi> in certain Decretal Epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtles, they haue abuſed the name of <hi>S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> to write of the Reuelation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head of Iohn Baptiſt, becauſe Reliques were profitable. They haue ſought profite by thruſtyng in a booke called <hi>Farrago Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monum,</hi> into <hi>S. Auſtens</hi> workes. And iiij. falſe quyers of paper into the Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople. Turnebus</hi> reporteth that for profite a couple of Gentlemen in hys countrey ſayde they were in hande with writyng of ſuch bookes as in déede they neuer went about to write, and that was for profite. And to conclud, where ſoeuer it bee, or howe daungerous ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be, how fooliſh ſoeuer it be, if there bee hope of profite, there they will bee, and there they wil ſéeke for aduauntage: as by cardyng, diſing, tablyng, poppet playing, ſtage playing, walkyng on rops, flying in the ayre, eatyng of poyſons, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng in the ſea, deluyng in the bowels of
<pb facs="tcp:132003:45"/> the earth, alcumiſtrie, lottaries, and ſuch like: but ſpecially at the Court and about the Court, For that from thence drope the rich golden apples,<note place="margin">In kynges Courtes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apples are moſt beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</note> there they thruſt in, and crowde in, There they créepe in, and burſt in, there is the world, there is all in all, there is the greateſt wealth of apples, and therefore there they are. Let "neuer princes thinke it otherwiſe. Thoſe that flocke about Courtes, they do it for apples, many for loue, but moſt for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditie. If the apples be in the South there they will be, if they be in the North, there they will be, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apples be gone they will all forſake the trée, if the apples be there they will clynge, &amp; watch, &amp; ward about it. And therfore watch cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cellors, preach preachers, &amp; pray people. That God will lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g mainteine, &amp; ſupport our good &amp; natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Prince Quéene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in all her Royalties, proprieties, wealthes, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, for if they can diſpoyle her of theſe, if they can plucke, and pil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere away the apples, they will ſoone brynge diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine vnto the trée: Though the trée be neuer ſo beautifull, and good, and though the roote therof be neuer ſo ſtedy and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, yet the eye of this wretched world alwayes gapeth after apples, &amp; ancreth
<pb facs="tcp:132003:45"/> onely vpon gaine.<note place="margin">Luke. 17.</note> Worldly men are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by worldly baytes, Eagles are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes houeryng about carryes, Beares about honny, Crowes about wormes, Bees about oyle, Wolues about ſhéepe, Foxes aboute pullyne, Kytes about gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bage, &amp; the world about aduauntage. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue not good Chriſten people that bee of wealth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt of them that ſéeme to loue you, they loue you, but for apples, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, truſt not theſe fawning, flering, flattering paraſites: what ſoeuer they ſay vnto you. If the dayes of heauen go fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, if your ſoules be brought low, it ſhall the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to late appeare, that they came to gayne, and gather, to plucke, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plume you, and when your apples are gone, &amp; your fruites miſſyng, if by ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng downe of your bodies, &amp; pluckyng vp of your rootes they may but warme them. They will do the beſt to ſtrike you downe &amp; by the rootes to plucke vp your families.</p>
            <p>My ſecond wordes in this caſe are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my brethren of the miniſtery, we are ſimple, and not ſo thoroughly trayned vp in the worlde as other be, our greateſt dread is not from the Papiſtes: becauſe we truſt them leſt: but there bee other
<pb facs="tcp:132003:46"/> apple gatherers, who myndyng coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous intentes, apples, and commodities yet profeſſyng holynes, godlines, and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall nature, they will perſuade you that your woordes are very ſpirite, that the holy ghoſt ſpeaketh in you, that they are edified onely by you, that ye haue the gift: but if they can once come by flat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teryng, and gloſyng to abuſe you, and when they haue ſo done, they will clappe their doores vppon you,<note place="margin">1. Kings. 13</note> as <hi>Ammon</hi> did to <hi>Thamar:</hi> They will wryng you, and trayne you to their purpoſe, and ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their will deſpiſe you. If you haue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples they will loue you, if you haue no apples, they will lothe you. My nexte ſpéech is to you Gentlemen of the Innes of Court, and elles where, your good wittes and good byrthes wyll not ſuffer me to leaue you vnadmoniſhed, you haue alſo apples for you are borne to landes, and lyue odes, your <hi>Delicta iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentutis</hi> call for expenſes, ſo that you are brought into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſurers handes, &amp; they as a ſpung will clenſe you, and wryng you. Vſurye is called in the Hebrew tounge <hi>Tocke</hi> and <hi>Tarbethe, Tocke</hi> ſignifieth loſſe, for there is none that meddeleth with it, but hee loſeth either bodely or
<pb facs="tcp:132003:46"/> ghoſtly. It is alſo called <hi>Tarbethe</hi> that is deceite, for the greateſt coſinage couin and colluſion that can be is in vſury, and in vſurers, vſury is ſayd to bite in the Scriptures, in déede it biteth, for it bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth you out of the Court into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, from ſilkes to ſacke cloth, from plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to penury. If you wilbe wiſe in tyme beleue not their money lent at a pinche their great dynners, and their ſwete en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteinementes, for in the ende they will but bite you. No beaſt by biting doth hurt (almoſt) except it be angry, but theſe men ſmilyng and ſmerkyng will bite you, and vndoe you. The bityng of a ſnacke may be cured with the herbe Dittanye. The bityng of a madde Dogge may be cured with a Crabfiſh: but the bityng of an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer is ſo chargeable that it is almoſt vncurable.<note place="margin">Vſurers.</note> The ſtyngyng of a Scorpion is healed with the body of a Scorpion brooſed into triacle, and ſurely me thinke the Magiſtrates ſhould doe right well if they woulde ſatiſfie all thoſe that haue bene bite by vſurers, either with their goods if they haue them, or els with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of their bodyes, if they haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not. God molifie their hartes, or breake their téeth, and direct men ſo in a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce
<pb facs="tcp:132003:47"/> of lyfe, that they light not into the mouthes of theſe Wolues. For ſurely they ſhalbe daungerouſly biten, whileſt you haue apples &amp; landes they will flocke about you, and cheriſh you, But when your apples and wealth is gone they will caſt you of, and abrenounce you.</p>
            <p>And now to the very laſt part of this Sermon, wherin I thinke it worthy the notyng, that God ſtyrreth vp the libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of men by cloudes and trées. There nedeth me thinketh no remembraunce to be kepte by houſe pictures, or Churche pictures, to ſtyrre vs vp to heauenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, for the heauen, the ayre, the earth, the ſea, are ful of ſuch creatures as may welbe our remembrauncers.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.</note> 
               <hi>The heauens declare the glorye of God,</hi> ſayth the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Diuinitie to be found out in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> the ſtarres may put vs in remembraunce of our vncleannes, ſithens that they are not cleane in Gods ſight. And of the omnipotencie of God, whiche out of the barren wombe of <hi>Sara</hi> did raiſe vp a people like vnto the ſtarres of heauen.<note place="margin">Gene. 15.</note> The Sunne and Moone may teach vs obedience in Geneſis. 1. whiche beyng once commaunded to moue neuer ceaſſed ſince the begynning of the world. The lightenyng may teach vs the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes<note place="margin">Math. 17.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:132003:47"/> of our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> the winde may put vs in remembraunce of the nature of the holy ghoſt, whiche bretheth where it liſt. The dew may bring vs in minde of peace and concorde,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> whiche is compared to the ſwete dewe of Hermon hill. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſée the Egle flye we may reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that God is able to take away our infirmities,<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> as he taketh away age from the Egle, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neweth her into youth. The Pellica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth put vs in minde of the ſolitarines y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are often driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o. The Storke in diſcretion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould haue in knowyng the time of our ſaluation.<note place="margin">Ierem. 8.</note> The voyce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Crane &amp; of the Swallow, may teach vs how poorly we ſhal ſpeake at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of our death.<note place="margin">Eſay. 38.</note> The Eſtredge runnyng away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her young ones, may teach vs the ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſome parentes, that wil get chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; not noriſh them.<note place="margin">Ierem. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment 4.</note> The Cocke crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may put vs in mynd of <hi>Peters</hi> offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; of <hi>Peters</hi> repentaunce.<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> The Henne ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together, &amp; ſhrouding of her chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens may put vs in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der hart of our ſauiour Chriſt towards vs.<note place="margin">Luke. 13.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 17.</note> The Partridge which vſeth to ſit vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other byrdes egges, is an Image of a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous man, that hordeth vp other mens goodes. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoeuer we ſée the lightnyng
<pb facs="tcp:132003:48"/> of a ſparrow we cannot but reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the prouidence of God.<note place="margin">Marke. 10.</note> The camell at a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels eye is the image of a couetous man at heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s gate. A bullocke being leadd to ſlaughter doth ſignifie a yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> folowing an harlot. An hind deſiring to drinke doth put vs in minde of the affection that our ſoules ſhould haue to God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.</note> A goate doth put vs in mynde of the ſeperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe in the day of Iudgement. A calfe doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber vs of the calues of our lippes, that is of prayer. The worme doth remember vs of our baſſenes. The piſemyer of la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.</note> The oxe and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſe of kyndnes for they knowe their maſter, and their cryb. The dogs of courteſie for they licked <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des.<note place="margin">Math. 16.</note> The vyne doth repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Chriſt, and the braunches vs. The oliue trée doth put vs in minde of an houſe wel furniſhed, with a vertuous wife and good childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Luke. 13.</note> The figge trée doth teach vs that thoſe are accurſed, whiche bring foorth no good frute.<note place="margin">Amos. 6.</note> Wormewoode doth put vs in mind of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nature of an ill Iudge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frute of Iuſtice into wormewood. The ſight of a lylly telleth vs we ſhould not bee carefull for braue apparell.<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> The groweth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> muſterdſede, teacheth vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of the kyngdome of God,<note place="margin">Luke. 13.</note> Cocle
<pb facs="tcp:132003:48"/> doth tell vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ſhall alwayes be wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of god in this life. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo did God ſometymes induce <hi>Iob</hi> to know God, &amp; him ſelf by theſe natural co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. As by the treaſures of his ſnow,<note place="margin">Iob. 38.</note> by the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dations of the earth, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doores of the ſea, by the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of <hi>Orion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Arctu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rus,</hi> By his thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring, by the nature of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crow, by the affections of the wild aſſe, by the gloriouſnes of the pecoke, by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the eſtridge, by the ſtrength of the horſe, by <hi>Behemoth</hi> &amp; <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> by the riſing of the hauke agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> South, and ſuch the like meanes. And ſo in this place <hi>Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> exhorteth vs to almes, and liberalitie by cloudes, and trées. <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>I heard thee, I did not ſo minde it, but now that I ſee thee in thy workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>I repent me and am ready to caſt duſt vppon me:</hi> As <hi>Iob</hi> whiche could not be moued by hearing, was allured to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, by the ſight of creatures: ſo you I dout not, though you do not mynde theſe arguments, which you haue heard from me with your eares: Yet the ſeyng of theſe creatures will make you mercyfull as cloudes, and plentyfull as trées, and teach you to gather good affections out of this ſchole of nature. In neceſſitie you
<pb facs="tcp:132003:49"/> ſhall finde it agayne, what ſo euer you diſburſe, what day ſo euer, come you ſhall haue made your frendes of your Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.<note place="margin">Luke. 16.</note> Which otherwiſe would haue ben occaſion of ſinne and iniquitie. The aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of thoſe poore men, whom you haue reliued with the bowels of mercy ſhall receiue you out of this vayne and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable world which fadeth,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2.</note> &amp; the luſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of into euerlaſtyng tabernacles whiche ſhall not periſhe nor the likyng thereof. Howbeit, this is not in your caſtyng or breakyng of bread, nor in your almes, déedes,<note place="margin">Rom. 9.</note> or workes, though for many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations you muſt do it. But in the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall paſſion, &amp; meritorious bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with the father and the holy ghoſt be all honor &amp; dominion for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>
               <hi rend="italic">FINIS.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:132003:49"/>
            <lg>
               <l>ROugh ſpeches ſeme rude, ſmooth ſpeches ar worſe:</l>
               <l>Forbearyng, and flatteryng (alas) we ſee</l>
               <l>Doth lead the world into Gods heuy curſe.</l>
               <l>If all were well what needes theſe wordes from me?</l>
               <l>That vices are helpt by ſmoothyng, and ſmilyng</l>
               <l>If any teache ſo: he meaneth beguilyng.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Though frendly warnynges folyes now appears:</l>
               <l>The day drawes on, the houre is hard at hand</l>
               <l>That you ſhall curſe eche cauſe that ſtoppt your ears:</l>
               <l>And made you kick to heare your vices ſcand.</l>
               <l>Ye fooles in hart that thinke there is no God,</l>
               <l>You ſhall know hym, by ſcourgynges of his rod.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
